<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>AI4Health</title>
    <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://cwcyau.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>AI4Health</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright © 2019 by Christopher Yau. All Rights Reserved.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://cwcyau.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>AI4Health</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the problem of early disease detection</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/earlydetection/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/earlydetection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The early detection of diseases is a highly desirable approach for addressing conditions where late stage disease cannot be easily treated or managed. Through early  detection, it maybe possible to take actions to minimise future disease severity or even prevent disease occurrence altogether. However, while the general concept is readily accepted, putting early detection into practice is often far from straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I will outline some ideas that can underpin a conceptual framework for developing early detection markers and point out some common mistakes. This is intended to provide a non-technical guide to some principles that might stimulate suitable study designs in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;disease-progression&#34;&gt;Disease progression&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I will introduce some terminology to make this discussion clearer. There will be frequent use of the phrase &lt;em&gt;disease progression&lt;/em&gt; to describe how a condition begins and typically worsens over time. The &lt;em&gt;disease state&lt;/em&gt; refers to the severity of the condition at any one moment in time and therefore, as a disease progresses, the disease state changes. Within this, I will refer to four different phases of disease progression:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pre-disease&lt;/strong&gt; which describes the period before the onset of the condition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Early stage&lt;/strong&gt; disease which covers the period between the onset of the disease and the earliest signs that the condition may have started to manifest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Established&lt;/strong&gt; disease typically describing the period when patients would likely be first diagnosed after clear symptoms have appeared and treatment is necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;late stage&lt;/strong&gt; disease which occurs after the disease has evolved and new courses of treatments are required. The long-term quality of life for the patient maybe severely diminished.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The type of diseases that we will be thinking about are chronic conditions (e.g. dementia) or disorders such as cancer. Short-term, readily curable diseases (e.g. the common cold) are not part of this discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;detecting-disease&#34;&gt;Detecting disease&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identifying a disease requires the ability to measure some quantity, known as a &lt;strong&gt;marker&lt;/strong&gt;, which is related to the disease state. The marker can be directly related to the disease, e.g. the size of a tumour on a CT scan, or an indirect marker such as an assessment of cognitive abilities in individuals with dementia. Markers that can directly measure disease state are preferred but indirect measurements may be the only pragmatic option in many situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;detection window&lt;/strong&gt; refers to the period when the magnitude of the marker exceeds a threshold and it is possible to detect the presence (or absence) of the marker (i.e. the minimum size of a breast tumour that can be seen on a mammogram). The detection window should be as wide as possible to give the best chance of picking up the disease. For early detection, it is necessary for the detection window to overlap with the early onset of the disease and the &lt;strong&gt;opportunity window&lt;/strong&gt; which is the period during which it maybe possible to intervene and influence the course of the disease progression (ideally, prevent it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;framework.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Framework&#34;&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 1. Progressive markers&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;types-of-early-detection-markers&#34;&gt;Types of early detection markers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of their potential for early detection, disease markers can broadly be classified into one of two forms (i) progressive and (ii) transient markers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Progressive markers&lt;/strong&gt; track the progression of the disease from early-onset to late-stage (Figure 1). They increase (or decrease) over time with the severity of the condition and do not ordinarily improve unless there is some medical intervention. The detection window opens as soon as the markers exceeds a certain threshold and does not close. For early detection, progressive markers should reach the detection threshold during the early phases of the disease giving the largest detection window possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;progress.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Progressive markers&#34;&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 1. Progressive markers gradually increase as the disease worsens, activating early during disease progression to give a large detection window that maximises the chance of overlapping with the opportunity window.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transient markers&lt;/strong&gt; are linked to features of the disease that are only active during certain periods of disease progression. The detection window is therefore bounded by both the period in which the marker is active and the detection threshold. As with progressive markers, the detection window for a transient marker ideally occupies an early phase of disease and overlaps the opportunity window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;transient.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Transient markers&#34;&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 2. An ideal transient marker activates at an early disease stage and during the opportunity window.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;common-mistakes&#34;&gt;Common mistakes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;not-all-valid-markers-are-early-detection-markers&#34;&gt;Not all valid markers are &amp;ldquo;early detection markers&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When developing a marker for early detection it is absolutely &lt;em&gt;crucial&lt;/em&gt; to understand the corresponding detection window and its relation to the opportunity window. For progressive markers, if the detection window does not overlap with early disease on-set and/or the opportunity window, the progression marker cannot be used to prompt early intervention. This can occur if the detection threshold is too high or the marker signal does not activate until the disease is well-established.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;progress-bad.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Poor progressive marker&#34;&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 3. Examples of unsuitable progressive markers for early detection. Top: the detection threshold is too high and the disease cannot be determined before the opportunity window ends. Bottom: The markers does not switch on until the opportunity window ends.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a transient marker is only active fleetingly this may leave an impractically short opportunity window which is not large enough to realistically catch patients at that critical moment of their disease progression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;transient-bad.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Poor transient marker&#34;&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 4. Unsuitable transient markers for early detection.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many investigations of early detection markers often fail to acknowledge that not all valid progressive or transient markers are suitable for early detection and characterising these property early can reduce wasted effort later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;case-control-discovery&#34;&gt;Case-control discovery&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A frequently used approach to identifying early detection markers is to compare a group of individuals with late stage disease (cases) and to those with early stage disease (controls). Markers that differ between the groups are then candidate early detection markers. However, this approach is &lt;em&gt;limited&lt;/em&gt;, since without any individuals occupying the intermediate stages of disease progression it is not possible to determine the detection window associated with the marker. The case-control study only tells us that the markers begin low in one group, and are high in the other. It does not tell us how quickly the marker reaches the detection threshold and therefore what the detection window is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;casecontrol.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Case control discovery of early detection markers&#34;&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 5. Early and late-stage patient comparisons can yield potential progressive markers but the full dynamic behaviour of the markers cannot be revealed without information from additional individuals occupying the intermediate stage of disease progression.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore the use of case-control type studies to identify early detection markers must be followed by validation studies to examine the dynamics of the potential markers to confirm and characterise their detection windows relative to the opportunity window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;association-is-not-prediction&#34;&gt;Association is not prediction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another issue with case-control studies is that some investigations often confuse association with prediction. Association in this instances means that there are markers which are more (or less) likely to occur in the case population than in the control population. For example, there maybe 40 in 1,000 late stage disease individuals who have a high-level of a blood protein marker, but only 5 in 1,000 early-stage individuals. We can then hypothesise that there maybe an &lt;em&gt;association&lt;/em&gt; of this marker with late-stage disease. It is tempting to extrapolate to this meaning that this is candidate early disease marker but extreme caution must be exercised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;casecontrol2.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Associated disease markers are not prediction markers&#34;&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 6. The green marker is present in most cases but hardly in any controls. A test based on this marker would give you high confidence about its results. The pink marker is associated with more cases than controls but if used as a basis for a test, the result would not be very reliable.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, what are the absolute numbers? Does the marker appear sufficiently often enough in the disease population to actually be practically useful? In this example, most individuals did not have the marker present. Can we narrow down those members of the population where the marker is more likely to be present? This might require a further study. Second, what is the predictive value of the marker? As described before, the case-control study highlights differences between your two groups of individuals but it does not tell you how the marker behaves in any individual over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;choosing-an-appropriate-comparator&#34;&gt;Choosing an appropriate comparator&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many investigations of early disease markers often use a seemingly obvious control group - individuals with no or early stage disease - but this may not be appropriate. For example, suppose we are examining whether changes in an individual&amp;rsquo;s retail spending patterns (e.g. store or credit card history) can be used to predict future cancer occurrence. It is reasonable to hypothesise that individuals with cancer could have exhibited early symptoms that led to more frequent purchases of off-the-shelf medications and health related products (e.g. pain relief, constipation relief, natural remedies). We might then wish to compare spend patterns between those with and without a cancer diagnosis. If a pattern exists, this signal could be exploited for early detection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;storecard.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Using frequency of retail encounters to predict cancer&#34;&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 7. The frequency of retail encounters from store card record could be tested for their predictive utility of future cancer diagnosis. Comparisons can be made as a naive control consisting of individuals who do not have cancer but also a robust control set containing individuals who have other conditions.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this approach excludes the possibility that changes in spending patterns could be induced by other, non-cancer conditions. While the spending pattern could clearly discriminate between those with and without cancer, is it specific enough to differentiate those who have cancer from someone who has a chronic but non-serious condition (such as irritable bowel syndrome)? Choosing the right comparator is important for determining the real-world utility of the putative early detection marker. In this example, a spending pattern which is induced by cancer but is not specific to cancer has limited utility due to the number of false alarms it could cause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;discussion&#34;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early detection of disease is a highly appealing and potentially extremely impactful. In this blog I tried to describe aspects of how I think about the problem and discussed some conceptual ideas for developing early detection approaches. Grappling with these concepts (and more that I did not have time to elaborate on) is critical to conducting effective research and development of early detection technologies, minimise wastage and ensuring resources are only focused on the most sounds ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MUM-PREDICT: HDRUK Team of the Year</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2022-12-31_mumpredict/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2022-12-31_mumpredict/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are proud to have been part of a glittering array of publications arising from our contribution to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://mumpredict.org/&#34;&gt;MUM-PREDICT&lt;/a&gt; projects over the last 12 months. The team also won the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hdruk.ac.uk/news/winners-announced-for-hdr-uks-annual-awards/&#34;&gt;Health Data Research UK Team of the Year 2022 award&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1186/s41512-022-00137-7&#34;&gt;Protocol for development and validation of postpartum cardiovascular disease (CVD) risk prediction model incorporating reproductive and pregnancy-related candidate predictors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Polypharmacy during pregnancy and associated risk factors: a retrospective analysis of 577 medication exposures among 1.5 million pregnancies in the UK, 2000-2019](&lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1186/s12916-022-02722-5%5D&#34;&gt;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1186/s12916-022-02722-5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://proceedings.mlr.press/v193/gadd22a.html&#34;&gt;mmVAE: multimorbidity clustering using Relaxed Bernoulli β-Variational Autoencoders&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bmjopen.bmj.com/content/13/2/e068718.abstract&#34;&gt;Maternal and child outcomes for pregnant women with pre-existing multiple long-term conditions: protocol for an observational study in the UK &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ML4H 2022</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2022-12-01_ml4h_2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2022-12-01_ml4h_2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to group members &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/gadd&#34;&gt;Charles Gadd&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/kim&#34;&gt;Woojung Kim&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/danks&#34;&gt;Dominic Danks&lt;/a&gt; on the following papers accepted at &lt;a href=&#34;https://ml4health.github.io/online_proceedings.html&#34;&gt;ML4H&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://neurips.cc/Conferences/2022&#34;&gt;NeurIPS&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://proceedings.mlr.press/v193/gadd22a.html&#34;&gt;mmVAE: multimorbidity clustering using Relaxed Bernoulli β-Variational Autoencoders&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://proceedings.mlr.press/v193/kim22a.html&#34;&gt;Feature Allocation Approach for Multimorbidity Trajectory Modelling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.08187&#34;&gt;A Multi-Resolution Framework for U-Nets with Applications to Hierarchical VAEs
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nature Communications Paper on personalised metabolic models</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2022-11-29_naturecomms/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2022-11-29_naturecomms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a collaboration led by Carles Foguet and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.inouyelab.org/&#34;&gt;Mike Inouye&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;../../author/yau&#34;&gt;Christopher Yau&lt;/a&gt; contributed to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-022-35017-7&#34;&gt;Genetically personalised organ-specific metabolic models in health and disease&lt;/a&gt; which has been published in Nature Communications.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Great UK PhD Data Science Survey</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/greatphdsurvey/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/greatphdsurvey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What am I doing?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My name is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wrh.ox.ac.uk/team/christoper-yau&#34;&gt;Christopher Yau&lt;/a&gt; and I am Professor of Artificial Intelligence at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ox.ac.uk&#34;&gt;University of Oxford&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hdruk.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;Health Data Research UK&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am carrying out a &lt;a href=&#34;https://forms.gle/u55swJNChHbaKMMS6&#34;&gt;survey&lt;/a&gt; of UK PhD students who are working in any area of data science and I need your help! We hope to get survey responses from over 300 PhD students so please help us by sparing 10-15 minutes of your time to answer some questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Responses received before &lt;strong&gt;15 July 2022&lt;/strong&gt; will be entered into a prize draw for a selection of £30 Amazon eGift cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 30 July 2022, data gathered through the survey will be analysed and a written report produced for distribution in September 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why another survey?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this survey is to improve our understanding of your motivations for doing a PhD, what you want to and are getting out of it, and where you want to go next. We know the world looks very different for data scientists than when I was doing my PhD so, with many exciting and lucrative opportunities coming from different parts of the ecosystem, what is the purpose of the PhD? What makes it an attractive qualification to have still?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know that the experience of PhD students varies due to several factors but – as data scientists - we need more detailed data to better understand and quantitatively characterise those variations. The survey information that will be collected will help us inform discussions with universities and funders to develop new strategies and approaches for doctoral training in the UK and to cater for changing needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the definition of data science being used? Who should take part?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you spend a large part of your research analysing real-world data, building computational models, or developing novel computer algorithms for analysing data then you should complete this survey. It does not matter if you are working on proteins, geology, or plasma physics, if it involves data then please complete this survey. If you largely work on theory and/or simulations relevant to data science but not much with data itself, we are keen to hear from you too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are there questions you’ve forgotten?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tried to include as many questions as possible without making the survey too laborious. There are many issues and topics we could have addressed but we made tough choices to focus on these key areas of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why is the last section only on health?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This survey is being conducted in partnership with Health Data Research UK – the national institute for health data research. They have a particular focus on health data science and consequently we have added a few questions on this area of work. However, though the findings will be directly linked to health data science, the responses should reveal insights into how inter-/multi-disciplinary research and career transitions are being supported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What about stipends and the cost-of-living crisis?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are deeply aware that UK PhD students are struggling with the current cost-of-living crisis and the impact of the real terms reduction in spending power offered by typical studentship stipends. We are not able to affect the decisions that must be taken by funders to address these issues but we hope that the survey information could shed light on some of the wider challenges faced by students in addition to financial support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why only UK?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would love to conduct a global survey but academic systems across the globe work quite differently and, as UK-based researchers working in the UK, it seems fitting that we would explore the nation in which we live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What will you do with the data?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will use the survey data to generate a report detailing our survey findings by September 2022. This will be disseminated publicly. All surveys are collected anonymously except where individuals choose to provide their name and e-mail address to be entered for the prize draw. Names and e-mail addresses submitted will only be used for this purpose and will not be shared for the analysis of the main survey data or for distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New report: My Cancer &amp; AI</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/mycancerai/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/mycancerai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A report on a patient engagement workshop series on what cancer patients think about artificial intelligence is now available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop series was developed in partnership with &lt;a href=&#34;https://ovarian.org.uk/&#34;&gt;Ovarian Cancer Action&lt;/a&gt; (OCA) as part of my Turing AI Fellowship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to patients and OCA for their support in developing this work and its impact on my future research plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The report is available to download from &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cwcyau/turingaifellowship/blob/c38556ef96768a3b83744ea7c9eabe3290ffc623/mycancerai.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AISTATS 2022</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2022-03-13_aistats_2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2022-03-13_aistats_2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to PhD student &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/danks&#34;&gt;Dominic Danks&lt;/a&gt; whose paper &lt;a href=&#34;http://aistats.org/aistats2022/accepted.html&#34;&gt;Derivative-Based Neural Modelling of Cumulative Distribution Functions for Survival Analysis&lt;/a&gt; has been accepted for presentation at &lt;a href=&#34;http://aistats.org/aistats2022&#34;&gt;AISTATS 2022&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An atlas of genetic scores to predict multi-omic traits</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2022-01-01_xu2022atlas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2022-01-01_xu2022atlas/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Derivative-Based Neural Modelling of Cumulative Distribution Functions for Survival Analysis</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2022-01-01_danks2022derivative/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2022-01-01_danks2022derivative/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EP-653 Diagnosing Acute Appendicitis using Machine Learning: A Systematic Review</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2022-01-01_chan2022ep/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2022-01-01_chan2022ep/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epidemiology of pre-existing multimorbidity in pregnant women in the UK in 2018: a population-based cross-sectional study</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2022-01-01_lee2022epidemiology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2022-01-01_lee2022epidemiology/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genetically personalised organ-specific metabolic models in health and disease</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2022-01-01_foguet2022genetically/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2022-01-01_foguet2022genetically/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In simulated data and health records, latent class analysis was the optimum multimorbidity clustering algorithm</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2022-01-01_nichols2022simulated/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2022-01-01_nichols2022simulated/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maternal and children&#39;s outcomes for pregnant women with pre-existing multiple long-term conditions: a study protocol of an observational study in the United Kingdom</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2022-01-01_lee2022maternal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2022-01-01_lee2022maternal/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Patient Derived Organoids Confirm That PI3K/AKT Signalling Is an Escape Pathway for Radioresistance and a Target for Therapy in Rectal Cancer</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2022-01-01_wanigasooriya2022patient/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2022-01-01_wanigasooriya2022patient/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rarity: Discovering rare cell populations from single-cell imaging data</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2022-01-01_marten2022rarity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2022-01-01_marten2022rarity/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Group relocation to Oxford.</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-12-22_oxford/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-12-22_oxford/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Christopher Yau will be relocating to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bdi.ox.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;Big Data Institute&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Oxford in February 2022 to take up a position as Senior Research Fellow between the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wrh.ox.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;Department of Women&amp;rsquo;s and Reproductive Health&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ndph.ox.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;Nuffield Department of Population Health&lt;/a&gt;. Future recruitment to the group for postdocs and students will be via the University of Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CIDER: an interpretable meta-clustering framework for single-cell RNA-seq data integration and evaluation</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-12-20_gbio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-12-20_gbio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our latest paper, based on the thesis work of former DPhil student Zhiyuan, has been published in Genome Biology. &lt;a href=&#34;https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-021-02561-2&#34;&gt;CIDER: an interpretable meta-clustering framework for single-cell RNA-seq data integration and evaluation&lt;/a&gt; describes a meta-clustering workflow based on inter-group similarity measures. We demonstrate that CIDER outperforms other scRNA-Seq clustering methods and integration approaches in both simulated and real datasets. Moreover, we show that CIDER can be used to assess the biological correctness of integration in real datasets, while it does not require the existence of prior cellular annotations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rarity: Discovering rare cell populations from single-cell imaging data</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-12-14_rarity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-12-14_rarity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Kaspar Martens will present his latest work at the NeurIPS Workshop &amp;ldquo;Learning Meaningful Representations of Life&amp;rdquo;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1r9TINxfXgB_cs4bOcT7ZYZjF5IMcb4X6/view&#34;&gt;Rarity: Discovering rare cell populations from single-cell imaging data&lt;/a&gt;. The work arises from his Turing-Crick Biomedical Award which supports a collaboration between the Alan Turing Institute and the Ciccarelli Group at Kings College London and the Francis Crick Institute.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NeurIPS 2021 Success - Multi-Facet Clustering Variational Autoencoders</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-12-07_mfcvae/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-12-07_mfcvae/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Christopher Yau has supported Health Data Research UK (HDRUK) PhD students Fabian Falck and Haoting Zhang in the development of work that has now been published as a paper at the NeurIPS 2021 conference. The work entitled &lt;a href=&#34;https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper/2021/hash/48cb136b65a69e8c2aa22913a0d91b2f-Abstract.html&#34;&gt;Multi-Facet Clustering Variational Autoencoders&lt;/a&gt; is a novel class of variational autoencoders with a hierarchy of latent variables, each with a Mixture-of-Gaussians prior, that learns multiple clusterings simultaneously, and is trained fully unsupervised and end-to-end. Chris, who directs the HDRUK PhD programme, writes about the work of the students in this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hdruk.ac.uk/news/the-different-facets-of-data/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yau receives award for ovarian cancer research</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-11-20_chfwrf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-11-20_chfwrf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.chfwrf.org/info/&#34;&gt;Columbia Hospital For Women Research Foundation&lt;/a&gt; have awarded &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/admin&#34;&gt;Christopher Yau&lt;/a&gt; the prize for most impactful paper in 2020 in the field of obstetrical and gynecologic and breast disease. The prize consisted of a $5,000 to a charity of Chris and Ahmed&amp;rsquo;s choosing and they selected &lt;a href=&#34;https://ovarian.org.uk/about-us/about-oca/&#34;&gt;Ovarian Cancer Action&lt;/a&gt; who co-funded the original work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cell.com/cancer-cell/pdf/S1535-6108(20)30042-8.pdf&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Repertoire of Serous Ovarian Cancer Non-genetic Heterogeneity Revealed by Single-Cell Sequencing of Normal Fallopian Tube Epithelial Cells.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; was a collaboration with the Ovarian Cancer Laboratory, led by Professor Ahmed Ahmed at Oxford. Chris and Ahmed co-supervised former group student &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/hu&#34;&gt;Zhiyuan Hu&lt;/a&gt;, who was lead author.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Artificial Intelligence Webinar - Ovarian Cancer Action UK</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-11-10_oca_video/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-11-10_oca_video/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/admin&#34;&gt;Christopher Yau&lt;/a&gt; worked with &lt;a href=&#34;https://ovarian.org.uk/&#34;&gt;Ovarian Cancer Action UK&lt;/a&gt; to put together a webinar on his research for patients and the public. You can find the video on Youtube: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kQ8m4L15GYM&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;What is artificial intelligence and what does it mean for cancer research?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiple postdoctoral research positions available</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-08-01_postdocs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-08-01_postdocs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have 4-5 two/three-year postdoctoral positions available linked to the following projects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../project/turingai&#34;&gt;Turing AI Fellowship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../project/optimal&#34;&gt;OPTIMAL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../project/mumpredict&#34;&gt;MuM-PreDICT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../project/roche-antibody&#34;&gt;Roche RPF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suitable applicants should either have experience in developing statistical and/or machine learning methods or a background in mathematics and computational science that would enable them to learn relevant research approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interested applicants are advised to examine recent group publications and projects to understand the research methods that have been adopted within the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be substantial opportunities to develop your individual research profile, leadership capabilities and link to a range of academic, clinical and industry partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All enquiries about vacancies should be addressed to the &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/admin&#34;&gt;Group Leader&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MuM-Predict</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/mumpredict/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/mumpredict/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The MuM-PreDiCT project has been successful in the funding call from the Strategic Priorities Fund (SPF): Tackling multimorbidity at scale: Understanding disease clusters, determinants &amp;amp; biological pathways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Strategic Priorities Fund (SPF) initiative, is jointly funded by the UKRI – MRC and the Department of Health and Social Care (DHSC), through the National Institute for Health Research (NIHR).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project will study and improve maternity care for women who are also managing two or more long-term health conditions. These can be both physical conditions, such as diabetes and raised blood pressure, and mental health conditions such as depression and anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our research team will develop statistical machine learning methods to analyse electronic health records from across all four nations comprising the UK. We will find out how many women have two or more long-term health conditions that presented before pregnancy and what health conditions they have. We will try and identify if factors such as age, weight, cultural or social background, level of education and number of previous pregnancies influences this. We will also find out which health conditions group together (cluster) during pregnancy, which clusters are most common and whether some clusters affect some women more than others.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OPTIMAL</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/optimal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/optimal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The OPTIMAL study is three-year study funded by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nihr.ac.uk/documents/artificial-intelligence-for-multiple-long-term-conditions-aim-programme-research-collaboration-stage-2-minutes/27578s&#34;&gt;NIHR AI for Multimorbidity&lt;/a&gt; and is a collaboration with the Universities of Birmingham and St Andrews with CPRD and University Hospitals Birmingham.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this study our group will develop novel artificial intelligence technologies to study electronic health records of individuals with two or more conditions known as &amp;ldquo;complex multimorbidity&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our aim is to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find the mix of diseases and drug treatments that interact over time to worsen or improve a patient’s health.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predict the next disease that people might develop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find drugs that help more than one disease.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work with patients, the public and health professionals to produce computer programs to help doctors improve the choice of drugs in patients with cMM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ICML 2021</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-07-18_icml_2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-07-18_icml_2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to PhD student &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/danks&#34;&gt;Dominic Danks&lt;/a&gt; whose paper &lt;a href=&#34;http://proceedings.mlr.press/v139/danks21a.html&#34;&gt;BasisDeVAE: Interpretable Simultaneous Dimensionality Reduction and Feature-Level Clustering with Derivative-Based Variational Autoencoders&lt;/a&gt;. has been accepted for presentation at the International Conference for Machine Learning 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roche ML for Antibody Design</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/roche-antibody/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/roche-antibody/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a new two-year collaboration with Roche, the group will be supporting a Roche Postdoctoral Fellowship in the development of antibodies. We will make use of Roche&amp;rsquo;s existing antibody data to develop machine-learning models generating sequences of antibodies with desired biophysical properties. Our aims are to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop machine learning models that ingest in-house antibody engineering data on antibodies to generate novel sequences with increased likelihood of desired biophysical properties,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Iteratively apply methods to antibody datasets,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborate with experimental teams to select and test model-generated candidate sequences in the wet lab,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Embed machine learning models in discovery processes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ECOSTAT &amp; ISBA 2021</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-06-26_isba_2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-06-26_isba_2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to PhD student &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/kim&#34;&gt;Woojung Kim&lt;/a&gt; whose will presenting his work on &amp;ldquo;Learning multimorbidity and its temporal dynamics with the Wright-Fisher Indian Buffet Processs&amp;rdquo; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmstatistics.org/EcoSta2021/&#34;&gt;EcoStat 2021&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://events.stat.uconn.edu/ISBA2021/&#34;&gt;International Society for Bayesian Analysis World Meeting 2021&lt;/a&gt; conferences.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New study in JCI Insights</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-05-04_ici_mara/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-05-04_ici_mara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://insight.jci.org/articles/view/147929&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Adipocyte-like signature in ovarian cancer minimal residual disease identifies metabolic vulnerabilities of tumor-initiating cells&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wrh.ox.ac.uk/research/ovarian-cancer&#34;&gt;Oxford Ovarian Cancer Cell Lab&lt;/a&gt; has been featured on the cover of JCI Insight. The work used methods developed by former group student &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/campbell&#34;&gt;Kieran Campbell&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD Opportunities 2021/22</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-04-23_epsrc_dtp_2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-04-23_epsrc_dtp_2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A new PhD projects is being advertised to join my group at the University of Manchester for the academic year 2021/22. Applications are due by &lt;strong&gt;21 May 2021&lt;/strong&gt; for the EPSRC Doctoral Training Programme. Successful applicants will receive funding support for their PhD studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[Explainable AI for Multimodal Data Integration in Biomedical Applications](&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.findaphd.com/phds/project/&#34;&gt;https://www.findaphd.com/phds/project/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.findaphd.com/phds/project/epsrc-dtp-explainable-ai-for-multimodal-data-integration-in-biomedical-applications/?p122456)&#34;&gt;https://www.findaphd.com/phds/project/epsrc-dtp-explainable-ai-for-multimodal-data-integration-in-biomedical-applications/?p122456)&lt;/a&gt;. Deadline: 21 May 2021.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>HDRUK PhD Director</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-04-01_hdruk_director/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-04-01_hdruk_director/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Health Data Research UK is pleased to announce the appointment of Professor Christopher Yau as Director of its HDRUK-Turing Wellcome PhD Programme in Health Data Science, starting 1 April 2021. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hdruk.ac.uk/news/christopher-yau-appointed-director-of-health-data-research-uk-turing-wellcome-phd-programme/)&#34;&gt;https://www.hdruk.ac.uk/news/christopher-yau-appointed-director-of-health-data-research-uk-turing-wellcome-phd-programme/)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Nature Reviews Methods Primer</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-01-14_bayesprimer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-01-14_bayesprimer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Christopher Yau and Kaspar Martens have contributed to an article &lt;em&gt;Bayesian statistics and modelling&lt;/em&gt; for the new Nature Reviews Methods Primer journal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s43586-020-00001-2&#34;&gt;Link to paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New study in Clinical Cancer Research</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-01-14_ccr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-01-14_ccr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With collaborators in the Oxford Ovarian Cancer Lab and Imperial College London, Zhiyuan Hu has identified that OxC-defined EMT-high SOCs carry particularly poor prognosis independent of established clinical parameters. She found these tumours are associated with high frequency of immunosuppressive macrophages, suggesting a potential therapeutic target to improve clinical outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://clincancerres.aacrjournals.org/content/early/2021/01/12/1078-0432.CCR-20-2782&#34;&gt;Link to paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New study in American Journal of Drug Alcohol Abuse</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-01-11_opioid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-01-11_opioid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Increasing rates of opioid-related overdose have been identified globally. Treatment for opioid use disorders (OUD) includes medications for opioid use disorder (MOUD) alongside behavioral support. In this study we use statistical analysis and machine learning to show that the Breaking Free Online program may reduce opioid use and improve biopsychosocial functioning in individuals with OUD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33428458/&#34;&gt;Link to paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adipocyte-like signature in ovarian cancer minimal residual disease identifies metabolic vulnerabilities of tumor initiating cells</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_artibani2021adipocyte/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_artibani2021adipocyte/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An interpretable meta-clustering framework for single-cell RNA-Seq data integration and evaluation</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_hu2021interpretable/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_hu2021interpretable/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Associations between baseline opioid use disorder severity, mental health and biopsychosocial functioning, with clinical responses to computer-assisted therapy treatment</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_elison2021associations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_elison2021associations/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BasisDeVAE: Interpretable Simultaneous Dimensionality Reduction and Feature-Level Clustering with Derivative-Based Variational Autoencoders</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_danks2021basisdevae/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_danks2021basisdevae/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian statistics and modelling</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_van2021bayesian/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_van2021bayesian/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CIDER: an interpretable meta-clustering framework for single-cell RNA-seq data integration and evaluation</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_hu2021cider/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_hu2021cider/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epidemiology of pre-existing multimorbidity in pregnant women in the UK in 2018: a cross-sectional study</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_lee2021epidemiology/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_lee2021epidemiology/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multi-facet clustering variational autoencoders</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_falck2021multi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_falck2021multi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pan-cancer detection of driver genes at the single-patient resolution</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_nulsen2021pan/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_nulsen2021pan/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Patient derived organoids reveal that PI3K/AKT signalling is an escape pathway for radioresistance and a target for therapy in rectal cancer</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_wanigasooriya2021patient/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_wanigasooriya2021patient/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Promises and challenges of adoptive T-cell therapies for solid tumours</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_morotti2021promises/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_morotti2021promises/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Protocol for the development of a core outcome set for studies of pregnant women with pre-existing multimorbidity</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_lee2021protocol/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_lee2021protocol/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Oxford Classic Links Epithelial-to-Mesenchymal Transition to Immunosuppression in Poor Prognosis Ovarian CancersOxC Accurately Identified Poor Prognosis in Ovarian Cancer</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_hu2021oxford/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2021-01-01_hu2021oxford/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Times Radio</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-12-05_timesradio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-12-05_timesradio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Christopher Yau appeared on the Hugo Rifkind on Times.Radio with Dame Janet Thornton and Tech Journalist Tom Chivers to discuss artificial intelligence and the recent AlphaFold2 development by Google Deepmind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thetimes.co.uk/radio/show/20201205-3541/2020-12-05&#34;&gt;Hugo Rifkind, Times.Radio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turing AI Acceleration Fellowship</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-11-27_turingai/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-11-27_turingai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Christopher Yau has been awarded a 5-year Turing AI Acceleration Fellowship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Turing AI Acceleration Fellowships are part of the government’s AI sector deal investment in Turing AI fellowships, recommended by the independent 2017 UK AI Review, whose report ‘Growing the artificial intelligence industry in the UK,’ was co-authored by Reguis Professor of Computer Science at Southampton, Dame Wendy Hall, and Jérôme Pesenti, now Vice President of AI at Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/20-million-boost-for-world-class-ai-research-could-transform-cancer-treatment-and-save-lives&#34;&gt;UK Government Press Release: &amp;ldquo;£20 million boost for world class AI research could transform cancer treatment and save lives&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ukri.org/news/new-turing-ai-fellows-to-deliver-world-class-ai-research/&#34;&gt;UKRI Press Release: &amp;ldquo;New Turing AI fellows to deliver world-class AI research&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-55099620&#34;&gt;BBC: &amp;ldquo;AI &amp;lsquo;doctor&amp;rsquo;s assistant&amp;rsquo; among projects given £20m&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turing AI Acceleration Fellowship</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/turingai/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/turingai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We aim to develop novel AI-driven predictive models that will allow us to describe how cancers evolve at the molecular level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aim to exploit the fact that cancers, whilst never exactly identical, often share similar development trajectories which we can learn about by collating information from across deep high-resolution molecular profiles of many cancers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By embedding our extensive biological knowledge of cancer within AI models, we will develop intelligent systems that will produce predictions that are more realistic, interpretable and better explain the progression of cancers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will help to improve the efficiency of drug development, decisions on treatment and to provide patients with more information about their illness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lead Investigator:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/admin/&#34;&gt;Christopher Yau&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD Opportunities 2021/22</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-10-22_mrc_dtp_2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-10-22_mrc_dtp_2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two new PhD projects are being advertised to join my group at the University of Manchester for the academic year 2021/22. Applications are due by &lt;strong&gt;15 November 2020&lt;/strong&gt; for the MRC Doctoral Training Programme. Successful applicants will receive funding support for their PhD studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.findaphd.com/phds/project/mrc-case-breaking-free-with-artificial-intelligence-using-data-driven-insights-to-improve-digital-health-support-for-substance-use-disorders/?p125142&#34;&gt;Breaking Free with Artificial Intelligence: using data-driven insights to improve digital health support for substance use disorders&lt;/a&gt;. Deadline: 15 November 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.findaphd.com/phds/project/mrc-dtp-ai-scbio-artificial-intelligence-for-single-cell-biology/?p122456&#34;&gt;AI-scBio: Artificial Intelligence for Single Cell Biology&lt;/a&gt;. Deadline: 15 November 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also opportunities in which I am co-supervisor:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.findaphd.com/phds/project/mrc-dtp-genomic-drivers-and-mechanisms-of-colorectal-peritoneal-metastasis-formation/?p125088&#34;&gt;Genomic drivers and mechanisms of colorectal peritoneal metastasis formation&lt;/a&gt;. Deadline: 15 November 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kcl.ac.uk/health/study/studentships/div-studentships/cancer/cruk-khp-phd-studentships-21&#34;&gt;CRUK KHP PhD studentships (based at Kings College London)&lt;/a&gt;. Deadline: 1 December 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hdruk.ac.uk/become-a-health-data-scientist/phd-programme/&#34;&gt;HDRUK Wellcome PhD Programme in Health Data Science&lt;/a&gt;. Deadline: 1 December 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scientists closer to finding the cell of origin for ovarian cancer</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-09-28_zh/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-09-28_zh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Former DPhil student Zhiyuan with the Ovarian Cancer Lab have created a new public engagement video showcasing our work on single cell sequencing of ovarian cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/oxfordahmedlab/status/1310686724402622464?s=20&#34;&gt;Scientists closer to finding the cell of origin for ovarian cancer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting guidelines to report the use of AI in clinical trials </title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-09-09_consortai/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-09-09_consortai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The CONSORT-AI and SPIRIT-AI Steering Groups (including Christopher Yau) have published their guidelines for conducting and reporting on clinical trials for AI interventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-020-1069-z&#34;&gt;Setting guidelines to report the use of AI in clinical trials&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Postdoc Opportunity with HDRUK</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-07-02_hdruk_mo/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-07-02_hdruk_mo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A new postdoc opportunity with myself and Dr Mike Inouye is available based in Cambridge:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jobs.cam.ac.uk/job/26181/&#34;&gt;Health Data Research UK (HDRUK) Multi-omics Consortium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD Opportunities 2020/21</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-06-24_mrc_case_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-06-24_mrc_case_2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A new funded PhD opportunity for UK/EU students is available to join my group for the academic year 2020/21:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.findaphd.com/phds/project/mrc-case-breaking-free-with-artificial-intelligence-using-data-driven-insights-to-improve-digital-health-support-for-substance-use-disorders/?p122456&#34;&gt;Breaking Free with Artificial Intelligence: using data-driven insights to improve digital health support for substance use disorders&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New eLife publication: A highly accurate platform for clone-specific mutation discovery enables the study of active mutational processes</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-05-21_digipico/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-05-21_digipico/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Bulk whole genome sequencing (WGS) enables the analysis of tumor evolution but, because of depth limitations, can only identify old mutational events. The discovery of current mutational processes for predicting the tumor&amp;rsquo;s evolutionary trajectory requires dense sequencing of individual clones or single cells. Such studies, however, are inherently problematic because of the discovery of excessive false positive mutations when sequencing picogram quantities of DNA. Data pooling to increase the confidence in the discovered mutations, moves the discovery back in the past to a common ancestor. Here we report a robust whole genome sequencing and analysis pipeline (DigiPico/MutLX) that virtually eliminates all false positive results while retaining an excellent proportion of true positives. Using our method, we identified, for the first time, a hyper-mutation (kataegis) event in a group of ∼30 cancer cells from a recurrent ovarian carcinoma. This was unidentifiable from the bulk WGS data. Overall, we propose DigiPico/MutLX method as a powerful framework for the identification of clone-specific variants at an unprecedented accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://elifesciences.org/articles/55207&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; is published in &lt;a href=&#34;https://elifesciences.org/&#34;&gt;eLife&lt;/a&gt; along with a &lt;a href=&#34;https://elifesciences.org/articles/57678&#34;&gt;commentary&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PHG Foundation - Artificial intelligence for genomic medicine</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-05-23_phg/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-05-23_phg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The PHG Foundation has published a report on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.phgfoundation.org/blog/genomics-and-artificial-intelligence&#34;&gt;Artificial intelligence for genomic medicine&lt;/a&gt;. Christopher Yau is very pleased to have been able to share his experience and insight into the subjects covered in this report.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD Opportunities 2020/21</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-03-26_phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-03-26_phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are two new funded PhD opportunities for UK/EU students available to join my group for the academic year 2020/21:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.findaphd.com/phds/project/epsrc-dtp-explainable-ai-for-multimodal-data-integration-in-biomedical-applications/?p120593&#34;&gt;Explainable AI for Multimodal Data Integration in Biomedical Applications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project will seek to develop explainable probabilistic machine learning methods for multimodal data integration for biomedical applications. We will consider a number of theoretical and practical issues with data integration and explainable AI and develop robust statistically sound solutions to these research problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://drive-health.org/apply/&#34;&gt;Multi-omics data integration for patient stratification in cancer clinical trials&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project aims to integrate these different types of data to derive correlative maps of the dynamic interplay in space and time between immune and tumour heterogeneity. The resulting molecular maps will then be associated with patient clinical data and response to treatment allowing to (1) identify key molecular players of resistance, reveal mechanistic insights and develop biomarkers of response and (2) inform strategies based on these biomarkers to prevent the onset of resistance and convert cold tumours into hot tumours responsive to immunotherapy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cancer Cell Publication</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-02-20_cancercell/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-02-20_cancercell/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/hu&#34;&gt;Zhiyuan Hu&lt;/a&gt; whose paper on the &amp;ldquo;The Repertoire of Serous Ovarian Cancer Non-genetic Heterogeneity Revealed by Single-Cell Sequencing of Normal Fallopian Tube Epithelial Cells&amp;rdquo; has been published in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cell.com/cancer-cell/fulltext/S1535-6108(20)30042-8&#34;&gt;Cancer Cell&lt;/a&gt;. Read press coverage by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dailymail.co.uk/health/article-7987639/Ovarian-cancer-hope-discovery-six-types-cell-trigger-silent-killer.html&#34;&gt;Daily Mail&lt;/a&gt; and the press release by the main funders &lt;a href=&#34;https://ovarian.org.uk/news-and-blog/news/ovarian-cancer-action-scientists-closer-finding-cell-origin-ovarian-cancer/&#34;&gt;Ovarian Cancer Action&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AISTATS 2020</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-01-17_kaspar/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-01-17_kaspar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/kaspar&#34;&gt;Kaspar Martens&lt;/a&gt; who has had two papers accepted into &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aistats.org/&#34;&gt;AISTATS 2020&lt;/a&gt;. Papers to be published soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A highly accurate platform for clone-specific mutation discovery enables the study of active mutational processes</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2020-01-01_karaminejadranjbar2020highly/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2020-01-01_karaminejadranjbar2020highly/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BasisVAE: Translation-invariant feature-level clustering with Variational Autoencoders</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2020-01-01_martens2020basisvae/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2020-01-01_martens2020basisvae/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploiting VDJ recombination of T cells to dissect the anti-cancer immune interactions in T cell lymphoma</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2020-01-01_murray2020exploiting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2020-01-01_murray2020exploiting/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genomic profiling in pancreatic cancer reveals spatial genetic heterogeneity but spatial transcriptomic homogeneity</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2020-01-01_sivakumar2020genomic/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2020-01-01_sivakumar2020genomic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guidelines for clinical trial protocols for interventions involving artificial intelligence: the SPIRIT-AI extension</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2020-01-01_rivera2020guidelines/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2020-01-01_rivera2020guidelines/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Has the COVID-19 Pandemic Changed How You Will Approach Research and Lab Work in the Future?</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2020-01-01_haynes2020has/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2020-01-01_haynes2020has/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neural decomposition: Functional anova with variational autoencoders</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2020-01-01_martens2020neural/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2020-01-01_martens2020neural/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The repertoire of serous ovarian cancer non-genetic heterogeneity revealed by single-cell sequencing of normal fallopian tube epithelial cells</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2020-01-01_hu2020repertoire/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2020-01-01_hu2020repertoire/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WIRED - Everyone should be worried by big tech&#39;s huge NHS data grab</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2019-12-16_wired/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2019-12-16_wired/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Christopher Yau talks about data anonymity and privacy concerns in this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wired.co.uk/article/google-apple-amazon-nhs-health-data&#34;&gt;Wired article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BIRM-CAM</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/birmcam/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/birmcam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christopher Yau is a co-investigator in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://birmcam.github.io/birmcam/&#34;&gt;BIRM-CAM&lt;/a&gt; project that is led by Professors Tom Marshall (University of Birmingham) and Sylvia Richardson (MRC Biostatistics Unit, University of Cambridge).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;multimorbidity&#34;&gt;Multimorbidity&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multimorbidity is when people suffer from more than one long-term illness. It is increasingly common as people live longer. It is important because individual illnesses have knock-on effects on others, it is more complex managing multiple than single illnesses, and multimorbid patients are heavy users of medications and health services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand multimorbidity we need to know which illnesses tend to occur together and which illness combinations most affect health. To adapt health services we need to know which types of people develop multimorbidity: their age, sex, ethnicity, socio-economic status and whether they tend to live in the same households. To learn how to prevent it we need to identify lifestyle factors (physical activity, diet, smoking, alcohol) linked to multimorbidity and the measurements (laboratory test results, weight, blood pressure) that might be early signs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;electronic-health-records&#34;&gt;Electronic Health Records&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electronic health records are a good source of information on multimorbidity because they include information on the same patient over many years. They include information on illnesses, medications, hospital admissions; measurements (laboratory tests, weight, blood pressure) and lifestyle (smoking, alcohol). Previous research has studied multimorbidity using a variety of statistical methods. It finds some illnesses, such as diabetes and heart disease tend to occur together. But different statistical methods often find different groups of illnesses. We need a single, consistent approach to this type of analysis to ensure we are researching the same groups of illnesses. Previous research generally has not made best use of all the available information. For example, patients are considered either to have or not have diabetes but research did not make use of laboratory measurements (such as blood glucose) identifying some people as likely to develop diabetes. Previous research grouped illnesses according to how commonly they occur together, without giving any special significance to combinations of illnesses linked to risk of death or hospital admission. Clearly such combinations of illness are of more importance. There are more advanced analysis methods which can address these and other shortcomings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-research&#34;&gt;The Research&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first part of our research will develop methods of data analysis. We will review research on different statistical methods for grouping illnesses together. We will hold a workshop involving leading UK researchers in the field to try to agree on the best approach to this type of analysis. Informed by this we will analyse two large databases of electronic health records, each including several million patients. In each database we will identify the groups of illnesses that co-occur and check our findings in the other database. This is considered good practice in analysis. At the end of this step we will produce software to analyse and find groups of illnesses in electronic health records and make this freely available for other researchers to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next part of our research will use additional information from two large surveys. Both surveys include details not always available in health records e.g. occupation, diet, lifestyle and measures of frailty. One includes 500,000 people the other has information on the same people over a period of 14 years. We will describe the consequences for patients of different combinations of illnesses: their levels of frailty because it is linked to need for social care; development of further illnesses; medications, use of health services and death. We will work with patient advisors to help guide analysis of patients journeys through health services. We will investigate possible causes of multimorbidity including people&amp;rsquo;s social circumstances, the environment, lifestyle (smoking, alcohol, diet and exercise) and laboratory test results that might help indicate causes. This step will point to the areas of environment and lifestyle which should be investigated further as possible causes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>HDRUK-Turing PhD programme</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2019-09-12_hdruk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2019-09-12_hdruk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Wellcome Trust have funded a new HDRUK-Turing Wellcome PhD programme in Health Data Science which will be jointly directed by Christopher Yau. Applications for entry October 2020 coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ICML 2019 SUCCESS!</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2019-07-01_icml/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2019-07-01_icml/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A paper by Kaspar Martens and group alumni Kieran Campbell Covariate GPLVM has been accepted for presentation at the International Conference on Machine Learning.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A descriptive marker gene approach to single-cell pseudotime inference</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_campbell2019descriptive/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_campbell2019descriptive/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Augmented ensemble mcmc sampling in factorial hidden markov models</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_martens2019augmented/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_martens2019augmented/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Author Correction: Reporting guidelines for clinical trials evaluating artificial intelligence interventions are needed</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_liu2019author/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_liu2019author/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian statistical learning for big data biology</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_yau2019bayesian/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_yau2019bayesian/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breaking Free with Artificial Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/breaking-free/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/breaking-free/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Using digital technology to improve health and care is now a priority focus for the UK National Health Service. New and maturing technological developments hold the potential to have a transformative effect on health service delivery. Digital health solutions can aid in the reduction of waiting times, more effective use of limited resources and improved treatment fidelity but, once such technologies are implemented, the dearth of data that can be acquired through their adoption itself presents a challenge. Data-driven insights, driven by machine learning and artificial intelligence techniques, can offer a glimpse of previously unknown patterns and identify opportunities for the development of new healthcare practices or policies. As digital health platforms become more sophisticated, the data that can be acquired often becomes more complex and heterogeneous, machine-based interpretation becomes a near-necessity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.breakingfreegroup.com/&#34;&gt;Breaking Free Group&lt;/a&gt; is a leading digital health and behaviour science company. Founded in 2010, it is formed from a team of psychologists, substance misuse experts and technology specialists. With an organisational philosophy built around the principles of state-of-the-art behaviour science and the UK Medical Research Council evaluation framework, they have developed a bespoke digital behavioural intervention platform that provides 24/7 access to a secure, GDPR-compliant, online digital cognitive behaviour therapy (CBT) platform with a particular focus on substance misuse. Users of the platform complete pre- and post-therapy questionnaires and interactive exercises designed to teach strategies to overcome addictive behaviours and improve wellbeing. Scoring on questionnaire responses can signpost users to personalised information sources. Real-time quantitative data from the platform can be anonymously fed to health service providers and commissioners for planning and policy development purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Breaking Free has seen its digital platform commissioned for use by the Ministry of Justice in UK prisons, Non-Government Charitable Organisations and NHS Trusts. Uniquely, Breaking Free operates under a research ethics protocol approved by the NHS Health Research Authority and endorsement by the National Institute of Clinical Excellence allowing the data they collect to be utilised for broader research applications. More recently, two new online platforms have been deployed more widely to the public targeting alcohol consumption reduction and smoking cessation. Breaking Free are based in both Birmingham and Manchester.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have initiated a new multi-disciplinary collaboration with the Breaking Free Online team to develop novel data science methodologies to exploit real-time digital health monitoring and intervention data. Our working exemplars will be based on the unique behavioural insights captured by the Breaking Free Group but the research outputs would have generic applicability in other related settings including youth mental health conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Convolutional filtering for mutation signatures</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/convsig/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/convsig/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mutation signatures are the hallmarks of mutagenic processes in cancer that can provide clues about the biochemical mechanisms by which DNA is altered in cancer. The extraction of such signatures from next generation sequencing data has traditionally been formulated as an unsupervised learning problem and solved using non-negative matrix factorization. We present an entirely novel approach based on convolutional filtering, inspired by technologies used in computer vision and image processing for genomic data analysis. We show that our approach has state-of-the-art performance compared to standard methods but also generalizes to allow consideration of larger sequence contexts using deep layering of convolutional networks providing a tool that could potentially reveal the impact of high-level genome structure on mutational density.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Researchers:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/feng/&#34;&gt;Yun Feng&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decomposing feature-level variation with covariate Gaussian process latent variable models</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_martens2019decomposing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_martens2019decomposing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep single-cell RNA-seq of the putative cell of origin revealed a novel molecular subtype of high-grade serous ovarian cancer with poor prognosis</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_hu2019deep/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_hu2019deep/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defective tubulin detyrosination causes structural brain abnormalities with cognitive deficiency in humans and mice</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_pagnamenta2019defective/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_pagnamenta2019defective/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Health Data Research UK-Turing PhD Programme</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/hdruk-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/hdruk-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hdruk.ac.uk/talent-training/hdr-uk-turing-phd-programme-funded-by-the-wellcome-trust/&#34;&gt;Health Data Research UK-Turing PhD programme in Health Data Science&lt;/a&gt; aims to develop future leaders in health data science. Its underlying philosophy is that health data science requires a combination of expertise spanning three fundamental areas: statistical, computational and health sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re looking for students who want to make a difference. People who want to work together to combine statistics and computation skills within a health setting to overcome existing challenges and look to develop new opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will develop your background in quantitative science (e.g. maths, statistics, physics, engineering, computing) and learn new skills within the health and biomedical communities, so that together you can undertake ground-breaking research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Co-Director:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/admin/&#34;&gt;Christopher Yau&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immunophenotypes of pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma: Meta-analysis of transcriptional subtypes</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_de2019immunophenotypes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_de2019immunophenotypes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Omics Network inference</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/monet/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/monet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dynamic alterations in gene expression programs during cell differentiation are regulated by the interplay of ubiquitous and tissue-specific transcription factors, and the epigenetic regulatory machinery. A mechanistic understanding can be postulated based on time-course multi-omics genome-wide measurements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We developed a novel Bayesian nonparametric regression approach called &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt;ulti-&lt;strong&gt;O&lt;/strong&gt;mics &lt;strong&gt;NET&lt;/strong&gt;work inference (MONET) for high-dimensionality multi-modal data integration to quantify the temporally dependent forces driving development and investigate by perturbation effects. Sparsity-inducing priors regularise the TF-gene interaction network and a Dirichlet process prior to regulate the number of participating TFs. This gives rise to a Bayesian nonparametric model where the number of TFs are learnt from data and not specified a priori. Statistical inference is performed in a Bayesian setting using an implementation of Hamiltonian Monte Carlo (HMC)-derived No-U Turn Sampler (NUTS) in STAN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We show that MONET is able to extract accurate time-dependent TF-gene interaction networks and assess the importance of each TF for the different stages in haematopoietic development. Our model allows us to make predictions on the importance of specific TF over time and under different perturbation settings. Based on this we can create hypotheses for intervention to improve efficiency or halt development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Researchers:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/rana/&#34;&gt;Anas Rana&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neural Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/neural-decomp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/neural-decomp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Neural network models for dimensionality reduction, such as Variational AutoEncoders (VAEs), can identify latent low-dimensional structures embedded within high-dimensional data. These low-dimensional representations can provide some insight into patterns within datasets but their interpretation relies on how these map back on the original feature set. However the latter requires interpreting what the decoder network has learnt which makes it challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, we have focused on understanding the sources of variation in Conditional VAEs. Our goal is to &lt;em&gt;decompose&lt;/em&gt; the feature-level variation in high-dimensional data through disentanglement of additive and interactions effects of latent variables and fixed inputs. We propose to achieve this through the &lt;em&gt;Neural Decomposition&lt;/em&gt; - an adaptation of the well-known concept of variance decomposition from classical statistics to deep learning models. We show that &lt;em&gt;identifiable&lt;/em&gt; Neural Decomposition relies on training models subject to constraints on the marginal properties of the neural networks whilst naive implementations will lead to non-identifiable models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Researchers:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/kaspar/&#34;&gt;Kaspar Maertens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Patient-specific cancer genes contribute to recurrently perturbed pathways and establish therapeutic vulnerabilities in esophageal adenocarcinoma</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_mourikis2019patient/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_mourikis2019patient/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Precision medicine and individual-level cancer driver genes</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/cancer-drivers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/cancer-drivers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The identification of cancer-promoting genetic alterations is challenging particularly in highly unstable and heterogeneous cancers. In collaboration with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.crick.ac.uk/research/labs/francesca-ciccarelli&#34;&gt;Ciccarelli Lab&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.crick.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;Francis Crick Institute&lt;/a&gt; we have developed a machine learning algorithm to identify cancer genes in individual patients considering all types of damaging alterations simultaneously. Analysing 261 EACs from the OCCAMS Consortium, we discover helper genes that, alongside well-known drivers, promote cancer. We confirm the robustness of our approach in 107 additional EACs. Unlike recurrent alterations of known drivers, these cancer helper genes are rare or patient-specific. However, they converge towards perturbations of well-known cancer processes. Recurrence of the same process perturbations, rather than individual genes, divides EACs into six clusters differing in their molecular and clinical features. Experimentally mimicking the alterations of predicted helper genes in cancer and pre-cancer cells validates their contribution to disease progression, while reverting their alterations reveals EAC acquired dependencies that can be exploited in therapy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Researchers:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/nulsen/&#34;&gt;Joel Nulsen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/misetic//&#34;&gt;Hrvoje Misetic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reporting guidelines for clinical trials evaluating artificial intelligence interventions are needed</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_consort2019reporting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_consort2019reporting/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RLevolution</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/rlevolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/rlevolution/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Genomic copy number evolution in cancer refers to the acquisition or loss of genome segments over time due to mutational processes in cancer that result in the loss of biological mechanisms for the maintenance of genome integrity in cells. Genome sequencing can allow us to detect these copy number alterations in cancer cells but do not directly inform us what the sequence of evolutionary events was that led to the present state of the cancer. We have developed a novel, first-of-its-kind reinforcement learning based approach for inferring evolutionary trajectories from genomic copy number profiles which we call \RLEvolution. We show that \RLEvolution is able to deconvolve the sequence of complex events that may occur during cancer evolution using a combination of simulated and real-world cancer datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Researchers:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/feng/&#34;&gt;Yun Feng&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Single-cell RNA sequencing with TCR repertoire profiling of mycosis fungoides</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_murray2019single/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_murray2019single/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Automatic BioData Scientist</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/neural-odes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/neural-odes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mathematical models of disease evolution seek to specify the complex mechanistic relationships between many measurable quantities over space and time. However, as our capability to generate experimental data improves, our ability to conceive of appropriate mathematical descriptions to describe biological phenomena has become a bottleneck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of machine learning is to “learn” complex dependencies automatically within data sets.  Neural networks (NNs) have been at the forefront of recent advances by offering a means of parametrising complex functional mapping between data and its representations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Novel computational machinery have enabled NN approaches to scale to the analysis of unprecedently large datasets and provide versatility over standard modelling approaches. However, despite their successes in a range of applications, in biomedical research, NNs are often derided for their “black box” discoveries, lack of interpretability and the need for unrealistic quantities of training data. Such criticisms often overlook the fact that default NN structures express no explicit assumptions about the problems on which they are applied and they are often used as generic data mining devices for discovery purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, there is a clear opportunity for the development of novel NN approaches that combine scalability and versatility with the capability of learning the physically realistic constraints that are embedded in hand-crafted mathematical models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project seeks to investigate the methodological foundations for what could form an &lt;em&gt;Automated BioData Scientist&lt;/em&gt; (AutoBioDataSci) platform. We would like to develop learning algorithms that can capture biological laws and encapsulate them in such a way that such knowledge can be transfer to new problems. This major project involves inter-linking representation learning theory with transfer and meta-learning as well as having its roots embedded in the biological scientific discovery process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Researchers:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/danks/&#34;&gt;Dominic Danks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/kaspar/&#34;&gt;Kaspar Maertens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Uncovering the long tail of oesophageal cancer driver genes for patient stratification</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_benedetti2019uncovering/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2019-01-01_benedetti2019uncovering/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DigiPico: A whole-genome sequencing approach to investigate microscopic residual chemotherapy resistance disease in ovarian cancer</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2018-01-01_karaminejadranjbar2018digipico/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2018-01-01_karaminejadranjbar2018digipico/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identification of Subtypes of Barrett&#39;s Esophagus and Esophageal Adenocarcinoma Based on DNA Methylation Profiles and Integration of Transcriptome and Genome Data Oesophageal Cancer Clinical and Molecular Stratification (OCCAMS) Consortium, May 2020, In: Gastroenterology. 158, 6, p. 1682-1697. e1 Research output: Contribution to journal&gt; Article</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2018-01-01_temelkovski2018identification/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2018-01-01_temelkovski2018identification/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrated single cell analysis reveals cell cycle and ontogeny related transcriptional heterogeneity in HSCs</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2018-01-01_povinelli2018integrated/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2018-01-01_povinelli2018integrated/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MixDir: scalable Bayesian clustering for high-dimensional categorical data</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2018-01-01_ahlmann2018mixdir/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2018-01-01_ahlmann2018mixdir/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NOX1 loss-of-function genetic variants in patients with inflammatory bowel disease</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2018-01-01_schwerd2018nox1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2018-01-01_schwerd2018nox1/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Probabilistic Boolean Tensor Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2018-01-01_rukat2018probabilistic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2018-01-01_rukat2018probabilistic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Separation of dual oxidase 2 and lactoperoxidase expression in intestinal crypts and species differences may limit hydrogen peroxide scavenging during mucosal healing in mice and humans</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2018-01-01_rigoni2018separation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2018-01-01_rigoni2018separation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuning microtubule dynamics to enhance cancer therapy by modulating FER-mediated CRMP2 phosphorylation</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2018-01-01_zheng2018tuning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2018-01-01_zheng2018tuning/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Uncovering pseudotemporal trajectories with covariates from single cell and bulk expression data</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2018-01-01_campbell2018uncovering/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2018-01-01_campbell2018uncovering/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A pan-cancer genome-wide analysis reveals tumour dependencies by induction of nonsense-mediated decay</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_hu2017pan/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_hu2017pan/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Abstract LB-158: Germline mutations in PALB2, BRCA1 and RAD51C observed in gastric cancer cases</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_sahasrabudhe2017abstract/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_sahasrabudhe2017abstract/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Boolean matrix factorisation</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_rukat2017bayesian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_rukat2017bayesian/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Colorectal cancer cell line proteomes are representative of primary tumors and predict drug sensitivity</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_wang2017colorectal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_wang2017colorectal/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Germline mutations in PALB2, BRCA1, and RAD51C, which regulate DNA recombination repair, in patients with gastric cancer</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_sahasrabudhe2017germline/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_sahasrabudhe2017germline/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Latin American Gastric Cancer Genetics Collaborative Group. Germline mutations in PALB2, BRCA1, and RAD51C, which regulate DNA recombination repair, in patients with gastric cancer</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_sahasrabudhe2017latin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_sahasrabudhe2017latin/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Probabilistic modeling of bifurcations in single-cell gene expression data using a Bayesian mixture of factor analyzers</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_campbell2017probabilistic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_campbell2017probabilistic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>switchde: inference of switch-like differential expression along single-cell trajectories</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_campbell2017switchde/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_campbell2017switchde/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing and learning on distributions with symmetric noise invariance</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_law2017testing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_law2017testing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hamming ball sampler</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_titsias2017hamming/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_titsias2017hamming/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unravelling cell cycle and ontogeny transcriptional heterogeneity in hematopoietic stem cells through integrated single cell RNA-seq</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_povinelli2017unravelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2017-01-01_povinelli2017unravelling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Abstract LB-340: A novel method for estimating somatic mutations cellular prevalence in cancer using whole genome haplotype phasing</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2016-01-01_chedom2016abstract/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2016-01-01_chedom2016abstract/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Order under uncertainty: robust differential expression analysis using probabilistic models for pseudotime inference</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2016-01-01_campbell2016order/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2016-01-01_campbell2016order/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ovarian Cancer</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/ovarian-cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/ovarian-cancer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are working with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wrh.ox.ac.uk/research/ovarian-cancer&#34;&gt;Ovarian Cancer Cell Laboratory&lt;/a&gt; led by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wrh.ox.ac.uk/team/ahmed-ahmed&#34;&gt;Professor Ahmed Ahsour Ahmed&lt;/a&gt; to unlock the molecular mechanisms underlying high-grade serous ovarian cancer (HGSOC) using genomics and bioinformatics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;premalignant-sox2-overexpression-in-the-fallopian-tubes-of-ovarian-cancer-patients&#34;&gt;Premalignant SOX2 overexpression in the fallopian tubes of ovarian cancer patients&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have discovered premalignant overexpression of SOX2 in the fallopian tubes of ovarian cancer patients which was nearly ubiquitous in HGSOCs. This was also a common feature in women with BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutations prior to ovarian cancer initiation. Thus, our data has important implications for screening, although it will need additional clinical evaluation to test the feasibility of quantitative detection of SOX2 expression or the expression of its downstream targets for this purpose. You can read the original research paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thelancet.com/journals/ebiom/article/PIIS2352-3964(16)30305-X/fulltext&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; as well as media reports &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dailymail.co.uk/health/article-3712949/Ovarian-cancer-detected-deadly-Scientists-identify-key-enzyme-makes-disease-spread.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.telegraph.co.uk/science/2016/07/28/ovarian-cancer-test-on-horizon-as-scientists-find-earliest-signs/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-unmasking-non-genetic-heterogeneity-through-by-single-cell-sequencing-of-fallopian-tube-epithelial-cells&#34;&gt;The unmasking non-genetic heterogeneity through by single-cell sequencing of fallopian tube epithelial cells&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently, we have used single cell sequencing to understand the inter-differentiation between cell states which promotes cancer cell survival under stress and fosters non-genetic heterogeneity (NGH). NGH is a surrogate of tumor resilience but its quantification is confounded by genetic heterogeneity. We showed that NGH can be accurately measured when informed by the molecular signatures of the normal cells of origin. We surveyed the transcriptomes of 4000 normal fallopian tube epithelial (FTE) cells, the cells of origin of serous ovarian cancer, and identified six FTE subtypes. We used subtype signatures to deconvolute SOC expression data and found substantial intra-tumor NGH that was previously unrecognized. Importantly, NGH-based stratification of ∼1700 tumors robustly predicted survival. Our findings lay the foundation for accurate prognostic and therapeutic stratification of SOC. You can read our Cancer Cell paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cell.com/cancer-cell/fulltext/S1535-6108(20)30042-8&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and press coverage from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dailymail.co.uk/health/article-7987639/Ovarian-cancer-hope-discovery-six-types-cell-trigger-silent-killer.html&#34;&gt;Daily Mail&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Researchers:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/hu/&#34;&gt;Zhiyuan Hu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pcaReduce: hierarchical clustering of single cell transcriptional profiles</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2016-01-01_zurauskiene2016pcareduce/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2016-01-01_zurauskiene2016pcareduce/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Premalignant SOX2 overexpression in the fallopian tubes of ovarian cancer patients: Discovery and validation studies</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2016-01-01_hellner2016premalignant/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2016-01-01_hellner2016premalignant/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Salt-inducible kinase 2 couples ovarian cancer cell metabolism with survival at the adipocyte-rich metastatic niche</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2016-01-01_miranda2016salt/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2016-01-01_miranda2016salt/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical inference in hidden Markov models using k-segment constraints</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2016-01-01_titsias2016statistical/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2016-01-01_titsias2016statistical/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Factors influencing success of clinical genome sequencing across a broad spectrum of disorders</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2015-01-01_taylor2015factors/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2015-01-01_taylor2015factors/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The alive particle filter and its use in particle Markov chain Monte Carlo</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2015-01-01_moral2015alive/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2015-01-01_moral2015alive/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ZIFA: Dimensionality reduction for zero-inflated single-cell gene expression analysis</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2015-01-01_pierson2015zifa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2015-01-01_pierson2015zifa/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A sequential algorithm for fast fitting of Dirichlet process mixture models</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2014-01-01_zhang2014sequential/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2014-01-01_zhang2014sequential/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Erythrocytosis associated with a novel missense mutation in the BPGM gene</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2014-01-01_petousi2014erythrocytosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2014-01-01_petousi2014erythrocytosis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hamming ball auxiliary sampling for factorial hidden Markov models</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2014-01-01_aueb2014hamming/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2014-01-01_aueb2014hamming/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Identification of Further Minimal Regions of Overlap in Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia Using High-Resolution SNP Arrays</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2014-01-01_knight2014identification/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2014-01-01_knight2014identification/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Towards Response Prediction Using Integrated Genomics in Chronic Lymphocytic Leukaemia: Results on 250 First-Line FCR Treated Patients from UK Clinical Trials</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2014-01-01_clifford2014towards/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2014-01-01_clifford2014towards/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Whole-genome sequencing of bladder cancers reveals somatic CDKN1A mutations and clinicopathological associations with mutation burden</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2014-01-01_cazier2014whole/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2014-01-01_cazier2014whole/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A decision-theoretic approach for segmental classification</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2013-01-01_yau2013decision/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2013-01-01_yau2013decision/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of colorectal cancers in British Bangladeshi identifies early onset, frequent mucinous histotype and a high prevalence of RBFOX1 deletion</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2013-01-01_sengupta2013analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2013-01-01_sengupta2013analysis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comprehensive genome-wide analysis of CLL samples from UK 1st line and relapsed/refractory clinical trials</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2013-01-01_robbe2013comprehensive/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2013-01-01_robbe2013comprehensive/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NucleoFinder: a statistical approach for the detection of nucleosome positions</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2013-01-01_becker2013nucleofinder/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2013-01-01_becker2013nucleofinder/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OncoSNP-SEQ: a statistical approach for the identification of somatic copy number alterations from next-generation sequencing of cancer genomes</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2013-01-01_yau2013oncosnp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2013-01-01_yau2013oncosnp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Survival in stage II/III colorectal cancer is independently predicted by chromosomal and microsatellite instability, but not by specific driver mutations</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2013-01-01_mouradov2013survival/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2013-01-01_mouradov2013survival/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantification of subclonal distributions of recurrent genomic aberrations in paired pre-treatment and relapse samples from patients with B-cell chronic lymphocytic leukemia</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2012-01-01_knight2012quantification/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2012-01-01_knight2012quantification/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian non-parametric hidden Markov models with applications in genomics</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2011-01-01_yau2011bayesian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2011-01-01_yau2011bayesian/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical Bayesian nonparametric mixture models for clustering with variable relevance determination</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2011-01-01_yau2011hierarchical/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2011-01-01_yau2011hierarchical/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A statistical approach for detecting genomic aberrations in heterogeneous tumor samples from single nucleotide polymorphism genotyping data</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2010-01-01_yau2010statistical/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2010-01-01_yau2010statistical/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genome-wide association study of CNVs in 16,000 cases of eight common diseases and 3,000 shared controls</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2010-01-01_wellcome2010genome/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2010-01-01_wellcome2010genome/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the utility of graphics cards to perform massively parallel simulation of advanced Monte Carlo methods</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2010-01-01_lee2010utility/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2010-01-01_lee2010utility/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presynaptic NMDARs in the hippocampus facilitate transmitter release at theta frequency</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2010-01-01_mcguinness2010presynaptic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2010-01-01_mcguinness2010presynaptic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative Whole Genome Analysis of Sequential Samples From Patients with B-CLL Identifies Novel Recurrent Copy Number Alterations Involving Critical B-Cell Transcription Factors</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2010-01-01_timbs2010quantitative/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2010-01-01_timbs2010quantitative/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing CNV detection methods for SNP arrays</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2009-01-01_winchester2009comparing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2009-01-01_winchester2009comparing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A genotype calling algorithm for the illumina beadarray platform</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2008-01-01_giannoulatou2008genotype/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2008-01-01_giannoulatou2008genotype/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A recursive, stochastic vessel segmentation framework that robustly handles bifurcations</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2008-01-01_allen2008recursive/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2008-01-01_allen2008recursive/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Akt regulates centrosome migration and spindle orientation in the early Drosophila melanogaster embryo</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2008-01-01_buttrick2008akt/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2008-01-01_buttrick2008akt/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Author Index Vol. 123, 2008</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2008-01-01_lionel2008author/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2008-01-01_lionel2008author/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CNV discovery using SNP genotyping arrays</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2008-01-01_yau2008cnv/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2008-01-01_yau2008cnv/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contents Vol. 123, 2008</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2008-01-01_lionel2008contents/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2008-01-01_lionel2008contents/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GenoSNP: a variational Bayes within-sample SNP genotyping algorithm that does not require a reference population</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2008-01-01_giannoulatou2008genosnp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2008-01-01_giannoulatou2008genosnp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical methodologies for the identification of copy number variation in mammalian genomes from high-throughput genomic datasets</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2008-01-01_yau2008statistical/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2008-01-01_yau2008statistical/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>QuantiSNP: an Objective Bayes Hidden-Markov Model to detect and accurately map copy number variation using SNP genotyping data</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2007-01-01_colella2007quantisnp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2007-01-01_colella2007quantisnp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative image analysis of chromosome dynamics in early Drosophila embryos</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2007-01-01_yau2007quantitative/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2007-01-01_yau2007quantitative/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Hidden Markov Models for Detecting Regions of Deletion and Duplication in the Human Genome using Illumina BeadChip Arrays</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2006-01-01_holmes2006bayesian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2006-01-01_holmes2006bayesian/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Application of NBS Labeling technology on cellular protein quantitation and identification</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2004-01-01_kesuma2004application/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2004-01-01_kesuma2004application/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Systematic Proteome analysis of breast cancer cell lines</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2004-01-01_ou2004systematic/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/publication/2004-01-01_ou2004systematic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Proposal</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-06-20_case-for-support-final/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-06-20_case-for-support-final/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project Title:&lt;/strong&gt; clinAIcan - developing clinical applications of
artificial intelligence for cancer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;track-record-max-2-pages&#34;&gt;Track Record [max 2 pages]&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am an Artificial Intelligence (AI) researcher with a focus on
developing computational and statistical methodologies for problems
within the biomedical and health sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research Contributions.&lt;/strong&gt; In &lt;em&gt;Statistics&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/em&gt;, my
major contributions have included i) expanding the statistical toolkit
for Markov models, ii) Bayesian nonparametric latent variable modelling
for high-dimensional data and iii) novel methodology for bioinformatics.
A significant feature of my work is the synthesis of statistical and
machine learning principles. I routinely published in both the major
machine learning conferences (NeurIPS, ICML, AISTATS)
[@aueb2014hamming; @law2017testing; @rukat2017bayesian; @rukat2018probabilistic; @martens2019decomposing; @martens2019ens; @martens2020nd; @martens2020trans]
as well as the most prominent statistical journals (JASA, JRSSB)
[@yau2011bayesian; @titsias2016statistical; @titsias2017hamming]
cross-fertilising ideas from both domains. These accomplishments have
been made while my primary role has been as a Principal Investigator
within medical faculties with responsibilities for a &lt;em&gt;genomic medicine&lt;/em&gt;
research programme that studies human disease - in particular, cancer.
This has involved supervision of experimental scientists, experimental
design as well as direct funding of these efforts. I have therefore
developed an array of integrated collaborations with biological and
clinical research groups within which my team has been embedded to carry
out this work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Academic Citizenship.&lt;/strong&gt; For the last five years, I have focused on my
young family which has limited my availability for international travel
and collaborations. During this period I have focused on supporting
early career researchers in my group and to maximise my national
identity through participation in a number of UK initiatives. This
platform gives me a strong basis to utilise this Fellowship to
accelerate my progress to an international leader in AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Genomics England.&lt;/em&gt; I founded and co-lead the Quantitative Methods,
Machine Learning and Functional Genomics Clinical Interpretation
Partnership (GeCIP) for the Genomics England (GEL) 100,000 Genomes
Project (100KGP) with Professor Martin Tobin (Leicester). This involves
coordinating and reviewing 100KGP research activities across a national
network of researchers on behalf of GEL as well as membership of the
scientific steering committee giving me deep insight into the developing
genomic medicine landscape in England. My work also involves advocacy
for genomic medicine, for example, I have recently contributed to the
PHG Foundation report on &amp;quot;Artificial intelligence for genomic
medicine&amp;quot; as well as organising an upcoming workshop on Machine
Learning and AI with GSK (due to held in July 2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Health Data Research UK/Alan Turing Institute.&lt;/em&gt; In 2019, I co-led (with
Professor Peter Diggle) a successful application on behalf of the Health
Data Research UK (HDRUK) and The Alan Turing Institute (Turing) for a
Wellcome PhD Programme in Health Data Science. This is a unique
multi-institutional PhD programme&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that is founded on HDRUK&amp;rsquo;s One
Institute vision of collective and collaborative working in health data
science. I am work package co-lead for artificial intelligence and
multimodal data integration in the HDRUK Multi-omics Consortium with Dr
Michael Inouye (Cambridge). I am also Principal Investigator of a Turing
Health Programme project, funded by a Strategic Priorities Fund AI for
Science and Government award, which provides matched support for the
work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;FLIER.&lt;/em&gt; I am a member of the Taskforce, consisting of senior academic,
government, NHS and industry representatives, that developed the Academy
of Medical Sciences (AMS) Future Leaders in Enterprise and Research
(FLIER) Leadership Programme. Here, I was able to utilise my analytical
and influencing skills to shape the format of the programme, challenging
our senior leaders to improve their understanding of the needs of those
in middle career stages and to boost the inclusivity and diversity
ambitions of this programme, in particular, by advocating the needs of
women in science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Other Activities.&lt;/em&gt; I am a member of the steering group for the
international CONSORT/SPIRIT-AI consortium where we are developing new
guidelines for the evaluation of AI-driven health interventions in
randomised control trials [@liu2019reporting]. I am applying knowledge
from this initiative as part of my contribution to the Phase 4 review
panel for the AI in Health and Care Award run by the AAC in partnership
with NHSX and NIHR. I also sit on the MRC Methodology Research Panel
where I have contributed to the development of MRC&amp;rsquo;s data science
strategy for its next funding cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Researcher Development.&lt;/em&gt; I have been fortunate to have trained and
mentored a fantastic group of students and postdoctoral fellows in the
last 8 years. Many have gone on to substantially AI and/or Data Science
related careers including in industry (2), independent research fellows
(4) or with academic faculty-level appointments (2). I am a strong
believer in developing &lt;em&gt;early independence&lt;/em&gt; opportunities for my
research team. I also sit on the Turing Institute Research Training and
Development Panel and and Advisory Group and act as a regular Academic
Mentor for Doctoral Students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research environment.&lt;/strong&gt; I was recently appointed as Chair in
Artificial Intelligence in Manchester as part of a university initiative
to substantially increase AI capability. This growth plan has also seen
the parallel recruitment of Professor Samuel Kaski, who has joined
Manchester as part of a joint professorship with Aalto University. Prof
Kaski is Director of the Artificial Intelligence Center of Finland which
hosts a European Laboratory for Learning and Intelligent Systems (ELLIS)
unit. Together with Professor Magnus Rattray (academic mentor, see
&lt;strong&gt;Institutional Support Letter&lt;/strong&gt;), Director of the Manchester Institute
for Data Science and AI and ELLIS Health Programme Fellow, we have
ambitious plans to make Manchester one of the most exciting UK hubs for
AI activity, particularly in Health. For example, the Christabel
Pankhurst Institute for Health Technology, is a new £25M investment
between the University and regional partners to provide a technology
translation and development hub for digital health which will be led by
Prof Kaski.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In cancer, the Manchester Cancer Research Centre (MCRC) (its Director
Professor Rob Bristow will be an academic mentor for my fellowship, see
&lt;strong&gt;Institutional Support Letter&lt;/strong&gt;) is a joint initiative between The
University of Manchester, Cancer Research UK and The Christie NHS
Foundation Trust. It has since been established as the cancer research
arm of the Manchester Academic Health Science Centre (MAHSC), which is a
strategic partnership between the University and six NHS Trusts across
Greater Manchester. The Cancer Research UK Manchester Institute (one of
only two &amp;ldquo;major&amp;quot; CRUK centres) and The Christie Hospital, the largest
single site cancer centre in Europe and the first UK centre to be
accredited as a comprehensive cancer centre treating more than 44,000
patients a year, are at the heart of the MCRC. The Paterson
Redevelopment Project will lead to the construction of a new
world-leading cancer research institute by 2030. Manchester is also part
of the CRUK International Alliance for Cancer Early Detection (ACED).
There are few locations in the UK with this combination of AI ambition
and core strengths in cancer and despite the immense challenges posed by
covid-19 for the university sector, the University of Manchester has
reaffirmed their institutional support for this fellowship proposal (1x
3yr Postdoc, 1x PhD, 0.5x RSE).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;proposed-research-and-context&#34;&gt;Proposed Research and Context&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;17pt&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;In the spring of 2012, I received the devastating diagnosis of
ovarian cancer - the &amp;lsquo;silent killer&amp;rsquo; Why me? Why anyone? Like
thousands of women before me, I searched for reasons WHY whilst trying
to come to terms with the illness.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;]{.roman} &amp;mdash; &lt;strong&gt;Patient 11152&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\vspace{4pt}
\vspace{0.2cm}
&lt;strong&gt;Ovarian Cancer.&lt;/strong&gt; Ovarian cancer (OvCa) affects approximately 7,000
women per year in the UK, with half over the age of 65. OvCa is hard to
detect, often presenting at an advanced stage making it extremely
difficult to treat. There has been little progress with improving
mortality rates in the last 20 years with 5-year survival rates as low
as 10-15% for the most common high-grade serous subtype (HGSOC). In
order to unlock the disease, international efforts have focused on
understanding the molecular determinants of the condition through new
technologies including -omics [@bowtell2010genesis].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My contributions have included being amongst the first to use
multi-region whole genome sequencing (WGS) to extensively characterise
the genetic heterogeneity &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; a single OvCa patient (Patient 11152)
and showing that an individual can harbour both chemotherapy-sensitive
and resistant cell populations (Figure
&lt;a href=&#34;#fig:patient_11152&#34;&gt;[fig:patient_11152]&lt;/a&gt;{reference-type=&amp;ldquo;ref&amp;rdquo;
reference=&amp;ldquo;fig:patient_11152&amp;rdquo;}(a)). We also identified an early
premalignant mutation in the &lt;em&gt;SOX2&lt;/em&gt; gene, which was found to be
frequently overexpressed in the fallopian tubes (FT) of OvCa patients
[@hellner2016premalignant]. We have used single cell RNA sequencing to
survey the cellular FT landscape of OvCa and showed that gene expression
patterns in the tumours can be traced back to those of certain FT cell
types [@hu2020repertoire]. This has allowed us to postulate that OvCa&amp;rsquo;s
can derive from different cell types within the FT and that the
cell-of-origin can drive significant differences in survival outcomes.
More recently, we have developed novel sequencing technologies to
examine &lt;em&gt;minimal residual disease&lt;/em&gt; (MRD) tumor samples that persist
after initial first-round treatments and repopulate the disease leading
to recurrence [@karaminejadranjbar2020highly]. This led us to
characterise genomic alterations, specific to one metastatic tumour
sample from Patient 11152 that had previously been uncharacterised by
standard sequencing. This provided evidence of the ongoing disease
evolution of the disease within the patient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\centering
&lt;img src=&#34;figs/patient11152.png&#34; alt=&#34;Telling the Story of Patient 11152. (a) Comprehensive multiregionand longitudinal tumour sampling and disease pathogenesischaracterisation for a single cancer patient was used to (b) determine apotential sequence of molecular events that occurred in the pathogenesisof her disease. &#34;&gt;{width=&amp;ldquo;85%&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[[fig:patient_11152]]{#fig:patient_11152 label=&amp;ldquo;fig:patient_11152&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vision.&lt;/strong&gt; Throughout this work, I have been struck by the many layers
of molecular complexity underlying OvCa that have been revealed by
advanced &amp;lsquo;omics technologies (multi-omics). Complexity that we have
begun to painstakingly unravel and enable clinicians and patients, like
11185, to better understand &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; their disease happened and &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; it
could be treated (Figure
&lt;a href=&#34;#fig:patient_11152&#34;&gt;[fig:patient_11152]&lt;/a&gt;{reference-type=&amp;ldquo;ref&amp;rdquo;
reference=&amp;ldquo;fig:patient_11152&amp;rdquo;}(b)). If this could be routinely
undertaken, not just for one patient, but &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; patient, we would
begin to realise the ambitions of cancer precision medicine: &lt;em&gt;to treat
patients at the right time in the right way&lt;/em&gt;. In this fellowship
proposal, I aim to investigate the fundamental AI technologies that
would enable the realisation of this ambition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;objectives&#34;&gt;Objectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;An understanding of the dynamics of cancer evolution might lead to
improvement in clinical outcomes, as it enables prognoses to be
accurately determined and &amp;rsquo;evolution-aware&amp;rsquo; patient management to be
applied.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; Turajlic &lt;em&gt;et. al.&lt;/em&gt; (2019), &lt;em&gt;Nature Reviews Genetics&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\vspace{0.5cm}
&lt;strong&gt;Overview.&lt;/strong&gt; Central to the realisation of this vision is the need for
a model of &lt;em&gt;molecular cancer progression&lt;/em&gt;. With a research team
assembled through this fellowship, given patient data, we would like to
be able to reconstruct the series of molecular events that have led to
their current state of disease and to use this model to predict the
future course of their disease under different treatment regimes (Figure
&lt;a href=&#34;#fig:overview&#34;&gt;[fig:overview]&lt;/a&gt;{reference-type=&amp;ldquo;ref&amp;rdquo;
reference=&amp;ldquo;fig:overview&amp;rdquo;}). My intention is not to study cancer
evolution in itself but to leverage the extensive pool of existing
knowledge derived over the last decade of cancer &amp;lsquo;omics research to
build computable models that could enable us to apply this knowledge in
a clinical setting [@swanton2020take]. I will centre my thinking around
ovarian cancer but the methodologies will be applicable to all cancers
and potentially other diseases that will be explored with a broad body
of project partners that I have assembled for this proposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\centering
&lt;img src=&#34;figs/project-overview.png&#34; alt=&#34;ProjectOverview.[]{label=&amp;amp;ldquo;fig:overview&amp;amp;rdquo;}&#34;&gt;{#fig:overview
width=&amp;ldquo;60%&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Existing work.&lt;/strong&gt; Longitudinal sampling represents the gold standard
for acquiring data to measure disease progression through repeated
sampling over time. However, in cancer this is rarely possible since
patients typically only present for diagnosis once signs and symptoms of
the disease have occurred and subsequent treatments will immediately
perturb the disease therefore preventing direct observation of the
natural evolution of the disease. We have overcome this limitation by
constructing models that exploit the asynchronous properties of cancer
patients within cross-sectional cohorts to recover &lt;em&gt;pseudotemporal&lt;/em&gt;
information about the dynamics of cancer evolution
[@campbell2018uncovering].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\centering
&lt;img src=&#34;figs/pseudotime.png&#34; alt=&#34;Latent variable models for cancer disease progression. Using (a)high-dimensional &amp;amp;lsquo;omics data from cross-sectional cohorts, we canidentify (b) low-dimensional manifolds which correspond to moleculardisease trajectories through the use of LVMs. (c) Our feature-leveldecomposition models [@martens2020nd] explicitly define a relationshipbetween the observed and latent space allowing us to interpret thesetrajectories in terms of the variation in the original measurablequantities. This is critical for precision medicine applications whichaim to target molecular mechanisms at the right stage of cancerprogression.[]{label=&amp;amp;ldquo;fig:pst&amp;amp;rdquo;}&#34;&gt;{#fig:pst
width=&amp;ldquo;90%&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Latent Variable Models.&lt;/em&gt; In terms of modelling, given a collection of
high-dimensional observation vectors ${ {\bf y}_1, \dots, {\bf y}_N }$
for $N$ individuals (Figure &lt;a href=&#34;#fig:pst&#34;&gt;[fig:pst]&lt;/a&gt;{reference-type=&amp;ldquo;ref&amp;rdquo;
reference=&amp;ldquo;fig:pst&amp;rdquo;}(a)), we assume that the data are noisy observations
that sit on embedded non-linear manifolds within the high-dimensional
observational space. These manifolds each correspond to a different
disease trajectory and distance along a manifold relates to the degree
of molecular progression (Figure
&lt;a href=&#34;#fig:pst&#34;&gt;[fig:pst]&lt;/a&gt;{reference-type=&amp;ldquo;ref&amp;rdquo; reference=&amp;ldquo;fig:pst&amp;rdquo;}(b)).
This can be captured by a hierarchical latent variable model:
$$\begin{aligned}
{\bf y}_n &amp;amp;= {\bf x}_n + {\bm \epsilon}_n, ~ n=1,\dots,N, \
{\bf x}_n &amp;amp;= {\bf f}({\bf z}_n(\tau_n), {\bf c}_n),\end{aligned}$$
where ${\bf x}_n$ corresponds to the noise-free observation, ${\bf z}_n$
are the coordinates in a low-dimensional latent space which is mapped to
the high-dimensional observation space via ${\bf f}$ and $\tau_n$ is a
unidimensional latent quantity denoting a notion of &amp;ldquo;distance&amp;quot; along
the manifold which we utilise as a measure of disease progression. Our
work has shown that such measures highlight molecular heterogeneity
amongst cancer patients that would be considered to be identical under
standard clinicopathlogical variables (Figure
&lt;a href=&#34;#fig:existing&#34;&gt;[fig:existing]&lt;/a&gt;{reference-type=&amp;ldquo;ref&amp;rdquo;
reference=&amp;ldquo;fig:existing&amp;rdquo;}(c)) Additional covariates of relevance are
captured by ${\bf c}_n$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Decomposable nonlinear dimensionality reduction.&lt;/em&gt; In statistical
machine learning, where ${\bf f}$ is treated as an unknown function,
popular models include the Gaussian Process [@lawrence2004gaussian] or
deep neural networks particularly in the form of Variational
Autoencoders (VAEs) [@kingma2014stochastic]. We have recently extended
both frameworks [@martens2019decomposing; @martens2020nd] to include
explicit additive structures on the mappings: $$\begin{aligned}
x_{pn} = f_{c}^p({\bf c}&lt;em&gt;n) + f&lt;/em&gt;{z}^p({\bf z}&lt;em&gt;n(\tau_n))  + f&lt;/em&gt;{cz}^p({\bf z}_n(\tau_n), {\bf c}_n), ~ p=1,\dots,P,\end{aligned}$$
which allow us to more precisely define the relationships between each
feature, the latent quantities and the covariates providing
interpretable structure which means ${\bf f}$ is not simply a black-box
(Figure &lt;a href=&#34;#fig:pst&#34;&gt;[fig:pst]&lt;/a&gt;{reference-type=&amp;ldquo;ref&amp;rdquo;
reference=&amp;ldquo;fig:pst&amp;rdquo;}(c)). This &lt;em&gt;feature-level interpretability&lt;/em&gt; means we
can understand the model in terms of how original features vary along
trajectories allowing experimental validation and the possibility of
biomarker tests to be developed to measure and confirm patient disease
progression (Figure
&lt;a href=&#34;#fig:existing&#34;&gt;[fig:existing]&lt;/a&gt;{reference-type=&amp;ldquo;ref&amp;rdquo;
reference=&amp;ldquo;fig:existing&amp;rdquo;}(a)). We have also extended these models to
incorporate scale- and translation-invariance allowing us to group
features exhibiting similar functional behaviour [@martens2020trans]
(Figure &lt;a href=&#34;#fig:existing&#34;&gt;[fig:existing]&lt;/a&gt;{reference-type=&amp;ldquo;ref&amp;rdquo;
reference=&amp;ldquo;fig:existing&amp;rdquo;}(b)). This enables the identification of
&amp;ldquo;pathways&amp;quot; or coordinated biological behaviour across many different
genes or proteins. These constraints have the benefit of promoting
adherence to biological reality whilst vastly reducing the feasible
model space meaning it is possible to learn effectively from the
relatively small data sets common in cancer studies such as the OXO-PCR
clinical trial (Figure
&lt;a href=&#34;#fig:existing&#34;&gt;[fig:existing]&lt;/a&gt;{reference-type=&amp;ldquo;ref&amp;rdquo;
reference=&amp;ldquo;fig:existing&amp;rdquo;}(c)).&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\centering
&lt;img src=&#34;figs/existing.png&#34; alt=&#34;Existing work. (a) Neural decomposition VAE [@martens2020nd]usesneural networks to provide a scalable Functional ANOVA type model withlatent variables. (b) BasisVAE [@martens2020trans] uses translation- andscale-invariant clustering of features to allow us to group samples andfeatures simultaneously (biclustering). (c) Application of our currentdisease progression models to the OXO-PCR OvCa trial cohort(unpublished).[]{label=&amp;amp;ldquo;fig:existing&amp;amp;rdquo;}&#34;&gt;{#fig:existing
width=&amp;ldquo;85%&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Work Packages.&lt;/strong&gt; Building upon this existing work, I propose two
AI-focused work packages to undertake detailed and novel research into
models to account for (i) treatment intervention and (ii) genetic
evolution. I then outline a decision making process in the third work
package to determine the specific clinical applications that we will
build using these technologies leveraging the interest and in-kind
contributions (total value: &amp;gt; £8M) of the large body of project
partners assembled in support. Note, for conciseness, I will not
specifically describe challenges related to the use of specific data
modalities (e.g. bulk vs single cell data). I believe my track record
provides evidence of my capability to address these issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\vspace{0.25cm}
{\it WP1: Mechanistically-driven latent variable models of  treatment interventions  [Years 1-3]}
. Our existing methodology has been beneficial for modelling the
&amp;ldquo;natural evolution&amp;quot; of untreated cancers but are not directly amenable
to data collected from post-treatment samples where the treatment may
have perturbed the progression of the disease (Figure
&lt;a href=&#34;#fig:treatment&#34;&gt;[fig:treatment]&lt;/a&gt;{reference-type=&amp;ldquo;ref&amp;rdquo;
reference=&amp;ldquo;fig:treatment&amp;rdquo;}(a)). Our goal is to &lt;strong&gt;construct models to
allow quantification of interventional effects at the molecular level&lt;/strong&gt;.
However, the &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; knowledge of the &lt;em&gt;absolute&lt;/em&gt; molecular effects of
the intervention is often poorly characterised and may only be defined
in qualitative terms, i.e. a drug acts to down-regulate the expression
of a particular pathway. This type of knowledge could be expressed in
terms of derivatives motivating a mechanistic approach:
$$\begin{aligned}
x_{pn}(\tau_n) &amp;amp;= \int_{-\infty}^{\tau_n} g^p({\bf x}_n(t), {\bf z}_n(t), t) d t, ~ p=1,\dots,P,\end{aligned}$$
where each observed feature is governed by a system of ordinary (or
potentially stochastic) differential equations (ODEs) $g$ whose
integration limits depend on an unobserved molecular time $\tau_n$. I am
therefore seeking to develop a novel class of &lt;strong&gt;mechanistically-driven
dimensionality reduction methods&lt;/strong&gt; (Figure
&lt;a href=&#34;#fig:treatment&#34;&gt;[fig:treatment]&lt;/a&gt;{reference-type=&amp;ldquo;ref&amp;rdquo;
reference=&amp;ldquo;fig:treatment&amp;rdquo;}(c)) where we wish to identify a
low-dimensional latent embedding for the data where the mapping from the
latent to observable space is governed by a dynamic model whose form is
not necessarily known but can be parameterised through deep neural
networks [@chen2018neural].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\centering
&lt;img src=&#34;figs/treatment.png&#34; alt=&#34;Mechanistic-driven models for quantifying treatment effects. (a)Treatments can act to push molecular states along the natural trajectoryof the disease or to perturb the disease on to a new trajectory. (b)Treatment effects need to be quantified on the feature-level in order tobe biologically and clinically interpretable. (c) A possible mechanisticapproach for modelling disease trajectories uses decoders within VAEsthat are constrained to behave like ODEs by matching derivatives throughthe decoder neural network to the ODE $g$. We have recently utilisedsuch ideas to develop neural network-based emulator for ODE solvers[@danks2020].[]{label=&amp;amp;ldquo;fig:treatment&amp;amp;rdquo;}&#34;&gt;{#fig:treatment
width=&amp;ldquo;85%&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will initially focus on ODEs that take the form: $$\begin{aligned}
\frac{ \partial x_p }{ \partial \tau }
&amp;amp;= g_p^p(x_p(\tau), {\bf z}(\tau)) + \sum_{q \neq p} g_q^p(x_q(\tau), {\bf z}(\tau)) + \sum_{q} g_{pq}^p(x_p(\tau), x_q(\tau), {\bf z}(\tau)) + \underbrace{I_p(x_p(\tau), z(\tau))}_{\mbox{\scriptsize Treatment}},\end{aligned}$$
which relates the time-evolution of each feature to itself, influences
from other features, feature-feature interactions and finally an
intervention term to account for treatment effects. The latter is of
interest since current cancer treatments are administered ignorant of
high-resolution molecular factors and therefore characterising the
molecular effects of current treatments is of interest. This setup will
allow the proposed work to build upon and &lt;strong&gt;integrate with hybrid
mechanistic-machine learning models for characterising drug
perturbations&lt;/strong&gt; on cancer cell lines that have established network
models of molecular interactions. These can be used as prior information
to regularise our models
[@oates2014causal; @korkut2015perturbation; @stewart2017integrating; @frohlich2018efficient; @yuan2019interpretable].
Note that these previous efforts are framed in a tightly regulated
setting under highly controlled experimental conditions. Our objective
is to address patient disease evolution and heterogeneity which are
factors not covered by previous studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work will also &lt;strong&gt;integrate causal approaches to establish
connections beween our mechanistic with structural causal models to
model the behaviour of systems under interventions&lt;/strong&gt;
[@mooij2013ordinary; @pfister2019learning; @peters2020causal]. We will
develop novel variants these concepts specific to understanding causal
relations in the presence of uncertainty in the molecular effects of
interventions. We will work with academic partners (see &lt;strong&gt;Data and
Experimental support&lt;/strong&gt;) to experimentally validate computational
predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\vspace{0.25cm}
{\it WP2: Reinforcement learning cancer evolution [Years 1-3]}
. Genome instability is a hallmark of many cancers, including OvCa,
which is said to be &amp;ldquo;copy number driven&amp;quot;
[@macintyre2018copy; @berger2018comprehensive; @the2020pan]. Loss of
genomic integrity in cancer cells leads to the accumulation of
chromosomal abnormalities - segments of DNA which are lost or duplicated
(Figure &lt;a href=&#34;#fig:rl&#34;&gt;[fig:rl]&lt;/a&gt;{reference-type=&amp;ldquo;ref&amp;rdquo;
reference=&amp;ldquo;fig:rl&amp;rdquo;}(a)). Remarkably, whilst copy number evolution has
been extensively studied
[@de2014spatial; @wang2014clonal; @gao2016punctuated] and genomic
instability is strongly linked to cancer outcomes
[@hieronymus2018tumor], there are currently no generative probabilistic
models that describe this phenomenon. Closely related work includes the
identification of tumour-specific phylogenies
[@caravagna2018detecting; @satas2020scarlet] or the use of Gillespie
simulations [@mcfarland2014tug; @lopez2020interplay] but these
approaches do not elucidate the low-dimensional representations we
require to encapsulate complex evolution processes that might give rise
to a so-called &lt;em&gt;evo/eco-index&lt;/em&gt; [@maley2017classifying].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modelling challenge lies in the fact that each copy number
alteration event that be described by a triplet of information: start
position, end position, alteration type. It is not a simple vectorisable
data type. Successive copy number alterations can overlap leading to a
different type of model requirement compared to that described in WP1
which is more suited to (near)continuous data types (gene expression,
proteins, metabolomics) rather than discrete DNA sequence data which
requires its own &amp;ldquo;arithmetic&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, my group has begun to develop novel &lt;em&gt;deep reinforcement
learning&lt;/em&gt; (Deep RL) approaches for learning probabilistic models of
genomic evolution [@feng2020]. The principle is that we can capture
evolutionary pressures through a &lt;em&gt;policy&lt;/em&gt; governing the Markov
transitions between genomic states (Figure
&lt;a href=&#34;#fig:rl&#34;&gt;[fig:rl]&lt;/a&gt;{reference-type=&amp;ldquo;ref&amp;rdquo; reference=&amp;ldquo;fig:rl&amp;rdquo;}(b)).
Evolution is treated as an &lt;em&gt;agent&lt;/em&gt; which takes &lt;em&gt;actions&lt;/em&gt; against the
genome causing it to mutate. The genome returns &lt;em&gt;rewards&lt;/em&gt; which are
related to the compatibility of that action with real world tumour copy
number profiles. Using RL we learn policies that allow us to generate
evolutionary event sequences which can give rise to biologically
realistic genomic copy number profiles (Figure
&lt;a href=&#34;#fig:rl&#34;&gt;[fig:rl]&lt;/a&gt;{reference-type=&amp;ldquo;ref&amp;rdquo; reference=&amp;ldquo;fig:rl&amp;rdquo;}(c)).
These trained models can then be used to retrospective infer
evolutionary histories given a tumour profile or to forward project the
evolution of the genome for predictive purposes. Importantly, in order
for such a model to be tractable, we need to incorporate prior knowledge
of actual biological mechanisms and constraints. Here, for example, we
require the notion of positivity (copy numbers cannot be negative),
whole genome duplications (WGD)
[@lopez2020interplay; @cross2020evolutionary] are a special action that
cause genomic content to double, invariant to arbitrary permutations of
the chromosome labelling, etc. Interestingly, to overcome the limited
number of real tumour profiles available (e.g. 300 from the TCGA OvCa
dataset), we have adopted notions of &lt;em&gt;self-play&lt;/em&gt; made prominent by
recent high-profile applications, such as &lt;em&gt;AlphaGo&lt;/em&gt;, to train our models
[@silver2017mastering].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\centering
&lt;img src=&#34;figs/rl.png&#34; alt=&#34;Reinforcement Learning for genomic copy number evolution. (a) Theobserved tumour genome is formed from a series of unseen copy numberalteration events which must be inferred. (b) The transitions betweeneach genomic state can be assumed to be Markovian and given by atransition probability distribution. (c) Inference can be framed as areinforcement learning problem to learn policies that describe thetransition probabilities.[]{label=&amp;amp;ldquo;fig:rl&amp;amp;rdquo;}&#34;&gt;{#fig:rl
width=&amp;ldquo;90%&amp;rdquo;}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this work package is to further &lt;strong&gt;develop a reinforcement
learning approach for genomic evolution&lt;/strong&gt; that has the scope and
scalability for later clinical applications. Since the number of
possible mutation types and the genome is enormous, we will
&lt;strong&gt;investigate scalable approaches to allow whole genome analysis with
high-resolution&lt;/strong&gt; (our current implementation is only operable at coarse
resolutions of a 1-5 megabases). This will include, for instance,
investigating &lt;strong&gt;the use of deep representation approaches for describing
large action and state spaces&lt;/strong&gt; [@chandak2019learning] that can be used
to derive analogous evolutionary progression time measures (to $\tau$ in
WP1). We will also explore novel variations on ideas such as action
elimination [@zahavy2018learn] or attention mechanisms to hone in on
copy number hotspots to reduce computational burden
[@vaswani2017attention]. Further, in order to capture evolutionary
divergence, &lt;strong&gt;we will extend the approach to allow tree-structured
mixtures of policies to model tumour heterogeneity&lt;/strong&gt;, integrating with
the extesive pre-existing work in this area, within a framework that
integrates other mutation types, notably point mutations (single
nucleotide variants, SNVs), giving rise to an ambitious attempt to
jointly model dual aspects of the evolving cancer genome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\vspace{0.25cm}
{\it WP3: Developing clinical applications [Years 4-5]}
. This work package will be broken down into distinct phases consisting
of an initial scoping exercise followed by three cycles of development
(see &lt;strong&gt;Work Plan&lt;/strong&gt;). During the scoping exercise, the capabilities
offered by the outputs of WP1 and WP2 will be introduced to the
potential user groups (clinician, patients, pharma) via a series of
engagement events. We will then identify a small number of realisable
exemplar applications that - in consultation with the Steering Group
(see &lt;strong&gt;Impact&lt;/strong&gt;) - will be developed during the remaining project
period. This work maybe carried out wholly by my research team or in
collaboration with the project partners leveraging in-kind support. Each
development phase will involve an agreed set of objectives that are
intended to be realised over a 3-6 month period. Each phase will end
with an evaluation period where next steps are agreed. A final series of
prototype evaluations will occur at the end of the Fellowship period.
This approach is specifically designed to leverage the opportunity
afforded by this fellowship scheme&amp;rsquo;s for flexible resource utilisation
in Years 3-5 and utilises the project partners to help define the most
impactful applications of our technologies and actively engage in
steering the project in Years 4-5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are however two possible applications that I can anticipate.
First, a &lt;strong&gt;clinical decision support (CDS) system to support
clinicians&lt;/strong&gt; involved in Molecular Tumour Boards (MTBs) in the
interpretation of complex &amp;lsquo;omics. This would be in supported within my
own institution via the digital Experimental Cancer Medicine Team&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
who have an ongoing programme of constructing decision support systems
to facilitate local MTB activities. We would leverage this existing
infrastructure to facilitate fast-track the movement of our research to
clinical applicability. Second, working with pharmaceutical partners, we
could &lt;strong&gt;integrate our methods into advanced clinical trial designs that
combine &amp;lsquo;omics profiling and AI-based progression modelling&lt;/strong&gt; to account
for treatment and outcome heterogeneity effects. This would be an
advance on current genomics-based cancer clinical trials which are
typically based on targeted gene panels or genomic regions and lack the
resolution to account for molecular heterogeneity within and between
patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data and Experimental support.&lt;/strong&gt; This work will be conducted in
collaboration with a number of clinical/academic labs (see &lt;strong&gt;Letters of
Support&lt;/strong&gt;). All laboratories have offered substantial in-kind support in
access to pre- and post-treatment molecular data sets from model systems
(cell lines, organoids, mice) and human patients using a range of
technologies (e.g WGS, RNAseq, IMC, methylation, nanopore, single-cell).
In addition, bioinformatics support and laboratory technician time have
been included to generate novel data sets where investigations require
additional data or novel biological insights have been uncovered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;national-importance&#34;&gt;National Importance&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The importance of this proposed work is underlined by the NHS Long Term
Plan which states that &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;linking and correlating genomics, clinical data
and data from patients provides routes to new treatments, diagnostic
patterns and information to help patients make informed decisions about
their care.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; [@england2019nhs; @health2019topol] Toward this, national
initiatives such as the GEL 100KGP, the NHS Genomic Laboratory Hubs and
the ISCF Accelerating Detection of Disease project are now beginning to
embed physical infrastructure within the health service to provide
routine -omics analysis capability. Within 10-15 years, we will expect
to see a revolution in the way in which the molecular characterisation
of disease, particularly cancer, will impact on routine clinical
practice with a matching requirement for intelligent analytics to
support its implementation. Further, there are a large number of
clinical cancer multi-omics initiatives occurring internationally (e.g.
The Tumor Profiler Study [@irmisch2020tumor]) so the UK is not alone in
this endeavour. Given this background, I believe this is the right time
to shape the analytical frameworks that will accompany the molecular
technologies to make use of the emerging data from this modernisation.
My combination of interests, expertise and integration into some of the
aforementioned initiatives therefore presents an opportunity to become
world leader in AI for clinical &amp;lsquo;omics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;impact-max-2-pages&#34;&gt;Impact [max 2 pages]&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research aims to advance a body of core AI technologies for
clinical applications of multi-omics for cancer progression modelling.
In order to maximise the impact of such developments, I have assembled a
body of charity (OCA), academic (Birmingham, Oxford, Kings/Crick,
Karolinska, UC Davis) and industry-based project partners (Roche, Astra
Zeneca, NEC Labs, Hummingbird Diagnostics) that will support the
translation of these ideas. The commitment of the partners is evidenced
by over £8M of specified in-kind contributions to the proposed project.
I will maintain relationships with project partners via three main
mechanisms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(i) Stakeholder Events.&lt;/strong&gt; I will host annual stakeholder engagement
meetings involving all project partners to review the progression of the
fellowship. Each meeting will be themed to focus on specific areas of
focus (Patient Engagement, Artificial Intelligence, Pharmaceuticals,
Clinicians and Patients) and timed to match project milestones. External
participants will be invited ensuring a broad representation of
stakeholders beyond those directly supporting this application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(ii) Secondments and Exchanges.&lt;/strong&gt; I have incorporated up to six months
of potential secondment/exchange time for members of the my research
team to participate in visits to project partners. These opportunities
will provide career enhancement experiences for the researchers
themselves, whilst at the same time providing a more intimate
opportunity to exchange and share ideas and progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(iii) Co-design and Steering Group.&lt;/strong&gt; A steering group will be
assembled from patient and project partner representatives. They will
oversee the main project start, mid-term and completion reviews. The
group will provide guidance and advice to myself and the project team
about the development of the project particularly with the areas of
impact to focus in toward the latter stages of the project (WP3). The
Steering Group chairs will be Institutional mentors, Professors Rattray
and Bristow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to impacts on clinical applications of cancer modelling as
outlined in the Work Packages, there are further specific areas of wider
engagement that I will develop:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patient and public engagement.&lt;/strong&gt; With Ovarian Cancer Action, I will
engage with patient stakeholders to raise awareness of the importance of
AI in the interpretation of complex &amp;lsquo;omics data and its role within an
emerging new paradigm for how cancer is diagnosed and treated. I will
also work with OCA to engage patient groups to understand the patient
perspective of our work. Does the ability to provide vastly more
detailed information about an individual&amp;rsquo;s disease lead to mental
overload? Does it help to remove the mystique about a diagnosis? How can
we better support clinician-patient interactions? This will underlie one
of the themed stakeholder events described above and leverage my
pre-existing work with OCA and the Oxford Ovarian Cancer Lab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Early Detection.&lt;/strong&gt; The generative models that we will develop will
simplify the process of &amp;ldquo;rolling back&amp;quot; to an earlier point in the
tumour development enabling putative early molecular changes to be
identified. This is of particular interest in Manchester which is part
of the CRUK-supported £55M International Alliance for Cancer Early
Detection (ACED).&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; All research conducted during this fellowship will
seek to align and exploit further funding opportunities and partnerships
within ACED. Further, I have also engaged with industry partner
&lt;em&gt;Hummingbird Diagnostics&lt;/em&gt;, who are developing liquid biopsy diagnostics
for early disease detection based on highly disease-specific miRNA
biomarkers. This partnership has the potential to see our AI
technologies supporting the actual development of novel biomarker tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other Data Modalities.&lt;/strong&gt; Two areas that this proposal has not
addressed are imaging and real-world evidence (RWE) using large-scale
clinical cancer data sets. Recent examples have highlighted the
importance of novel AI in these areas.
[@alaa2018autoprognosis; @shen2020learning; @bica2020real; @abduljabbar2020geospatial].
As a member of the Strategy Advisory Group for the Health Programme at
The Alan Turing Institute, I am currently advising on a potential
strategic partnership between the Turing and a global pharmaceutical
company. This partnership would provide opportunities for research
collaboration, access to domain expertise and valuable sources of RWE
data linking -omics to clinical trials. If this application is
successful, I would use the fellowship to engage with this partnership,
if and when Turing successfully concludes negotiations&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Further, in
medical imaging, I have engaged with the EU ERA &amp;ldquo;Advancing Breast Cancer
histopathology towards AI-based Personalised medicine&amp;quot; consortium
(ABCAP), led by the Karolinska Institutet (see &lt;strong&gt;Support Letter&lt;/strong&gt;), who
are developing AI methodology for automating screening of routine
histopathology images. In collaboration we would co-develop joint models
for molecular and image-based disease progression characterisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;equality-diversity-and-inclusion&#34;&gt;Equality, diversity and inclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Career development.&lt;/strong&gt; The project has been designed to ensure all
researchers have equal opportunity to take leadership over work
components as well as training to further their career potential. Each
work package has been designed to be led by each of the three PDRAs (see
&lt;strong&gt;Work Plan&lt;/strong&gt;). Thesis projects for PhD students would be shaped to work
across work packages giving students the opportunity to develop a unique
synthesis of ideas whilst allowing PDRAs the opportunity to share in
mentorship and supervisory responsibilities. All PDRAs and students will
have the opportunity to have up to six months experience outside of the
main project to develop collaborations with external stakeholders.
Organisation of themed stakeholder events will be led by the research
team members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ovarian Cancer and Gender.&lt;/strong&gt; For OvCa, it is evident that for a
disease which, predominantly impacts women only, a female voice should
be integral to every aspect of its delivery.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Working with Ovarian
Cancer Action and our institutional Athena Swan team, we will work to
actively promote the research opportunities to female researchers
(noting that they are under-represented in AI as well). Every team
member will receive training from the charity to ensure they develop a
deep understanding of the disease and its wider impacts. These
individuals would develop as an Ambassador for the project and be
central to our dissemination plans both internally and externally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integration with external activities.&lt;/strong&gt; As co-Director of the
HDRUK-Turing PhD Programme, I am actively involved in developing
innovative approaches to improving research culture including EDI. This
is required by Wellcome for the award of the programme but also couples
with the missions of the two national institutes. I will endeavour to
leverage the broader scale of EDI activities associated with this
programme within my fellowship to obtain the critical mass needed to
inspire real change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Responsible research and innovation.&lt;/strong&gt; Genomic medicine is motivated
by the understanding that human disease is driven by molecular factors,
including genetics, and treatments should be adapted to these features
which may differ from patient to patient. Stratification by molecular
features can lead to differential treatment strategies that could
incidentally correlate with sub-groups of the human population including
sub-group designations which associate with sex or ethnicity. There is
increasing evidence that the molecular traits of cancer are related to
ancestry [@li2020genomic]. Sensitivity and an understanding of the wider
implications of these issues must be at the heart of all work in this
area and the development of artificial intelligence techniques is no
exception. Towards this goal, I have initiated a specific collaboration
with Professor Carvajal-Carmona at the UC Davis Comprehensive Cancer
Centre (see &lt;strong&gt;Support Letter&lt;/strong&gt;) who have an extensive track record of
work in genetics and cancer research in ethnic minorities groups and
other causes of disparity in California and Latin America. Recently,
they have been supported by NIH to establish patient-derived animal and
cellular cancer models for &amp;lsquo;omics profiling specifically from ethnic
minority groups. There are no such equivalent projects in the UK and
therefore this exemplar stands out as an opportunity for my team and
partners to learn best practice and considerations for responsible
engagement across communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;impact-of-covid-19&#34;&gt;Impact of covid-19&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the impact of covid-19 on the UK health system and economy, I
have understandably not attempted to obtain direct support from NHS
organisations at this challenging time. In addition, OCA are unable to
commit financial support for this research at this time as had been
previously discussed during the outline stage. If the fellowship is
awarded, I will re-engage with discussions at a later date. Finally,
over the last 10 weeks, I have spent the majority of my time providing
home schooling and childcare for my daughter with only limited time
available for this application alongside regular academic
responsibilities. I am &lt;em&gt;not alone&lt;/em&gt; in facing these challenges but wish
to voice the impact on covid-19 on productivity on all applicants with
care responsibilities during these challenging and unprecedented times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\printbibliography
0.75&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\endgroup&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consisting of Queen&amp;rsquo;s Belfast, Birmingham, Cambridge, Edinburgh,
Manchester, Oxford and University College London&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;URL:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cancerresearchuk.org/about-cancer/find-a-clinical-trial/a-study-help-doctors-predict-who-will-respond-well-paclitaxel-chemotherapy-cancer-ovary-oxo-pcr-01&#34;&gt;https://www.cancerresearchuk.org/about-cancer/find-a-clinical-trial/a-study-help-doctors-predict-who-will-respond-well-paclitaxel-chemotherapy-cancer-ovary-oxo-pcr-01&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://digitalecmt.org/&#34;&gt;https://digitalecmt.org/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ACED:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cancerresearchuk.org/funding-for-researchers/research-opportunities-in-early-detection-and-diagnosis/international-alliance-for-cancer-early-detection&#34;&gt;https://www.cancerresearchuk.org/funding-for-researchers/research-opportunities-in-early-detection-and-diagnosis/international-alliance-for-cancer-early-detection&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anticipated agreement date: Q4 2020&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men can carry heritable genetic mutations that lead to increased
risk of ovarian cancer.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
