<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>About on AI &amp; Data Science Group</title>
    <link>/blogs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in About on AI &amp; Data Science Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 22:27:21 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/blogs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/blogs/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 22:42:51 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blogs/about/</guid>
      <description>Group Leader: Christopher Yau</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Academic Mentorship</title>
      <link>/blogs/mentoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 22:42:51 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blogs/mentoring/</guid>
      <description>Turing I am available to support Turing-based students in the following areas:
 Managing student-supervisor relationships. I have supervised numerous students to completion but I am also young enough to still remember what being a student is like! Happy to provide a helpful ear or work on strategies with you. Career planning. There are great careers out there but maximising your opportunities requires early thought and planning. Get ahead. Fellowship/job application review.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>explAIn</title>
      <link>/blogs/explain/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 22:42:51 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blogs/explain/</guid>
      <description>The Multidisciplinary Team (MDT) When a patient is diagnosed with cancer, a group of health professionals will work together to plan their treatment. This is called a multidisciplinary team (MDT). The constitution of the team will depend on the type of cancer but may include a surgeon, a cancer doctor (oncologist), a haematologist, and a clinical nurse specialist. The MDT will meet to discuss the results of any tests and to plan treatment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/blogs/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 22:26:13 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blogs/research/</guid>
      <description>Overview Our research is primarily concerned with the development of statistical and machine learning methodologies with a particular focus on applications in the biomedical sciences.
A complete list of publications can be found on [Google Scholar] (https://scholar.google.co.uk/citations?user=5tyrt68AAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en) and our research software is available on Github
Cancer Tumour heterogeneity describes the genetic diversity both within (intra-tumour heterogeniety) and between tumours (inter-tumour heterogeneity). Genetic differences within and between tumours give rise to different disease outcomes and patient responses to therapies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Join Us</title>
      <link>/blogs/join/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 22:26:09 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blogs/join/</guid>
      <description>Postdoctoral [September 2019] Postdoctoral opportunities are available at the University of Manchester. Please contact the group leader to enquire.
PhD Admissions are currently being taken through the following study programmes at the University of Manchester, please see the websites for more details:
 University of Manchester Doctoral Training Programmes China Scholarship Council Wellcome PhD Programme in Health Data Science  Potential applicants are encouraged to speak to the Group Leader before making applications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/blogs/blog5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blogs/blog5/</guid>
      <description>Academic Mentorship       code{white-space: pre;} pre:not([class]) { background-color: white; }  if (window.hljs) { hljs.configure({languages: []}); hljs.initHighlightingOnLoad(); if (document.readyState &amp;&amp; document.readyState === &#34;complete&#34;) { window.setTimeout(function() { hljs.initHighlighting(); }, 0); } }  h1 { font-size: 34px; } h1.title { font-size: 38px; } h2 { font-size: 30px; } h3 { font-size: 24px; } h4 { font-size: 18px; } h5 { font-size: 16px; } h6 { font-size: 12px; } .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>News</title>
      <link>/blogs/news/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blogs/news/</guid>
      <description>WIRED - Everyone should be worried by big tech&#39;s huge NHS data grab - 16 December 2019 Christopher Yau talks about data anonymity and privacy concerns in this Wired article.
HDRUK-Turing PhD programme - APPLICATIONS OPEN - 18 November 2019 Applications are now open for the HDRUK-Turing Wellcome PhD programme in Health Data Science.
New student - Dominic Danks - 1 October 2019 Welcome to our new Turing PhD student, Dominic Danks who joins us following a MSc in Computational Statistics and Machine Learning at University College London and an MSci in Theoretical Physics from the University of Birmingham.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>