<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>About on Yau Group</title>
    <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in About on Yau Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 22:27:21 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 22:42:51 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/about/</guid>
      <description>Group Leader: Christopher Yau</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 22:26:13 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/research/</guid>
      <description>Overview Our research is primarily concerned with the development of statistical and machine learning methodologies with a particular focus on applications in the biomedical sciences.
A complete list of publications can be found on Google Scholar and our research software is available on Github
Cancer Tumour heterogeneity describes the genetic diversity both within (intra-tumour heterogeniety) and between tumours (inter-tumour heterogeneity). Genetic differences within and between tumours give rise to different disease outcomes and patient responses to therapies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Join Us</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/join/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 22:26:09 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/join/</guid>
      <description>Philosophy My mission is to provide an environment for those who want to become strong and independent life-long learners.
I am interested in hearing about great ideas and providing the environment and support in which you can pursue them. This maybe during your time working within my group but it could also mean preparing you for life once you leave.
I want to empower you to pursue ambitious research by identifying subject matters that stimulate you and providing the tools to critically evaluate and self-direct your own work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>News</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/news/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/news/</guid>
      <description>AISTATS Success! - 24 December 2018 Congratulations to Kaspar Martens whose paper Augmented Ensemble MCMC sampling in Factorial Hidden Markov Models (joint work with Michalis Titsias) was accepted for presentation and publication in the proceedings of AISTATS 2019.
PhD Studentships - 17 December 2018 PhD studentships with the Alan Turing Institute and the MRC IMPACT programme are available for the academic year 2019. For more information see the University of Birmingham ATI Studentship and MRC IMPACT.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>