<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>About on Yau Group</title>
    <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in About on Yau Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 22:27:21 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 22:42:51 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/about/</guid>
      <description>Group Leader: Christopher Yau</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 22:26:13 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/research/</guid>
      <description>Overview Our research is primarily concerned with the development of statistical and machine learning methodologies with a particular focus on applications in the biomedical sciences.
A complete list of publications can be found on Google Scholar and our research software is available on Github
Cancer Tumour heterogeneity describes the genetic diversity both within (intra-tumour heterogeniety) and between tumours (inter-tumour heterogeneity). Genetic differences within and between tumours give rise to different disease outcomes and patient responses to therapies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Join Us</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/join/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 22:26:09 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/join/</guid>
      <description>Postdoctoral Research Fellows [10 November 2018] Three postdoctoral positions will soon be available for researchers interested in statistical machine learning based in Birmingham and at the Alan Turing Institute. Contact the Group Leader for details.
PhD Admissions are currently being taken through the following study programmes, please see the websites for more details:
 MRC IMPACT Doctoral Training Programme Alan Turing Institute  Potential applicants are encouraged to speak to the Group Leader before making applications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>News</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/news/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/blogs/news/</guid>
      <description>PhD Studentships - 17 December 2018 PhD studentships with the Alan Turing Institute and the MRC IMPACT programme are available for the academic year 2019. For more information see the University of Birmingham ATI Studentship and MRC IMPACT.
Quantitative Systems Biology 2018 - 9 November 2018 Christopher Yau gave an invited talk at the QSBW 2018 workshop organised by Kings College London students.
Conference paper presentation - 2 October 2018 Former ERASMUS student Constantin Alhmann-Eltze presented his paper MixDir: Scalable Bayesian Clustering for High-Dimensional Categorical Data.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>