<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cancer | Yau Research Group</title>
    <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/tag/cancer/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://cwcyau.github.io/tag/cancer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Cancer</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://cwcyau.github.io/media/icon_hu_91b8b2faea5b4fd3.png</url>
      <title>Cancer</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/tag/cancer/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal Survival Analysis with Locally Deployable Language Models</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/event/survival-llm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/event/survival-llm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our research explores how artificial intelligence can improve medical prognosis while protecting patient privacy. We developed a lightweight, locally deployable large language model (LLM) that predicts patient survival by combining information from clinical text, medical records, and genetic data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike traditional AI systems that depend on cloud computing, our model runs entirely on-site, making it suitable for hospitals with limited computing resources and strict data-security requirements. It not only provides accurate, calibrated survival predictions, but also generates concise, human-readable explanations that help clinicians understand the reasoning behind each estimate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tested on real cancer patient data, our approach outperforms existing survival models and demonstrates that trustworthy, interpretable AI can be achieved without compromising privacy or accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lead Investigator:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/admin/&#34;&gt;Christopher Yau&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GPerturb in Nature Communications</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2025-07-01_gperturb/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2025-07-01_gperturb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/xing&#34;&gt;Hanwen Xing&lt;/a&gt; on having his paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-025-61165-7&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;GPerturb: Gaussian process modelling of single-cell perturbation data&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; accepted in Nature Communications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Single-cell RNA sequencing and CRISPR screening enable high-throughput analysis of genetic perturbations at single-cell resolution. Understanding combinatorial perturbation effects is essential but challenging due to data sparsity and complex biological mechanisms. We present GPerturb, a Gaussian process-based sparse perturbation regression model designed to estimate gene-level perturbation effects. GPerturb employs an additive structure to separate signal from noise and captures sparse, interpretable effects from both discrete and continuous responses. It also provides uncertainty estimates for the presence and strength of perturbation effects on individual genes. We demonstrate the use GPerturb on both simulated and real-world datasets, characterising its competitive performance with current state-of-the-art methods. Furthermore, the model reveals meaningful gene-perturbation interactions and identifies effects consistent with known biology. GPerturb offers a novel approach for uncovering complex dependencies between gene expression and perturbations and advancing our understanding of gene regulation at the single-cell level.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MLCB 2024</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2024-08-16_mlcb_2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2024-08-16_mlcb_2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/gadd&#34;&gt;Charles Gadd&lt;/a&gt; on having his paper accepted at &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/cs.washington.edu/mlcb2024/home?authuser=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MLCB 2024&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changes in the number of copies of certain parts of the genome, known as copy number alterations (CNAs), due to somatic mutation processes are a hallmark of many cancers. This genomic complexity is known to be associated with poorer outcomes for patients but describing its contribution in detail has been difficult. Copy number alterations can affect large regions spanning whole chromosomes or the entire genome itself but can also be localised to only small segments of the genome and no methods exist that allow this multi-scale nature to be quantified. In this paper, we address this using Wave-LSTM, a signal decomposition approach designed to capture the multi-scale structure of complex whole genome copy number profiles. Using wavelet-based source separation in combination with deep learning-based attention mechanisms. We show that Wave-LSTM can be used to derive multi-scale representations from copy number profiles which can be used to decipher sub-clonal structures from single-cell copy number data and to improve survival prediction performance from patient tumour profiles.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper in Bioinformatics</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2023-12-13_rarity_2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2023-12-13_rarity_2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/martens&#34;&gt;Kaspar Martens&lt;/a&gt; on having his paper accepted in &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/bioinformatics/article/39/12/btad750/7471872?login=false&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bioinformatics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cell type identification plays an important role in the analysis and interpretation of single-cell data and can be carried out via supervised or unsupervised clustering approaches. Supervised methods are best suited where we can list all cell types and their respective marker genes a priori, while unsupervised clustering algorithms look for groups of cells with similar expression properties. This property permits the identification of both known and unknown cell populations, making unsupervised methods suitable for discovery. Success is dependent on the relative strength of the expression signature of each group as well as the number of cells. Rare cell types therefore present a particular challenge that is magnified when they are defined by differentially expressing a small number of genes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typical unsupervised approaches fail to identify such rare subpopulations, and these cells tend to be absorbed into more prevalent cell types. In order to balance these competing demands, we have developed a novel statistical framework for unsupervised clustering, named Rarity, that enables the discovery process for rare cell types to be more robust, consistent, and interpretable. We achieve this by devising a novel clustering method based on a Bayesian latent variable model in which we assign cells to inferred latent binary on/off expression profiles. This lets us achieve increased sensitivity to rare cell populations while also allowing us to control and interpret potential false positive discoveries. We systematically study the challenges associated with rare cell type identification and demonstrate the utility of Rarity on various IMC datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Implementation of Rarity together with examples is available from the Github repository (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kasparmartens/rarity%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://github.com/kasparmartens/rarity)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New publication in BMC Bioinformatics</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2023-11-30_picocnv_2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2023-11-30_picocnv_2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/nulsen&#34;&gt;Joel Nulsen&lt;/a&gt; on having his paper accepted in &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1186/s12859-023-05576-7&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BMC Bioinformatics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genomic insights in settings where tumour sample sizes are limited to just hundreds or even tens of cells hold great clinical potential, but also present significant technical challenges. We previously developed the DigiPico sequencing platform to accurately identify somatic mutations from such samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, we complete this genomic characterisation with copy number. We present a novel protocol, PicoCNV, to call allele-specific somatic copy number alterations from picogram quantities of tumour DNA. We find that PicoCNV provides exactly accurate copy number in 84% of the genome for even the smallest samples, and demonstrate its clinical potential in maintenance therapy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PicoCNV complements our existing platform, allowing for accurate and comprehensive genomic characterisations of cancers in settings where only microscopic samples are available.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MLCB 2023</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2023-08-16_mlcb_2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2023-08-16_mlcb_2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/martens&#34;&gt;Kaspar Martens&lt;/a&gt; on having his paper accepted at &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/cs.washington.edu/mlcb2023/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MLCB 2023&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generative models for multimodal data permit the identification of latent factors that may be associated with important determinants of observed data heterogeneity. Common or shared factors could be important for explaining variation across modalities whereas other factors may be private and important only for the explanation of a single modality. Multimodal Variational Autoencoders, such as MVAE and MMVAE, are a natural choice for inferring those underlying latent factors and separating shared variation from private. In this work, we investigate their capability to reliably perform this disentanglement. In particular, wehighlight a challenging problem setting where modality-specific variation dominates the shared signal. Taking a cross-modal prediction perspective, we demonstrate limitations of existing models, and propose a modification how to make them more robust to modalityspecific variation. Our findings are supported by experiments on synthetic as well as various real-world multi-omics data sets. The paper is available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://proceedings.mlr.press/v240/martens24a.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PMLR&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New report: My Cancer &amp; AI</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/mycancerai/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/mycancerai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A report on a patient engagement workshop series on what cancer patients think about artificial intelligence is now available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop series was developed in partnership with &lt;a href=&#34;https://ovarian.org.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ovarian Cancer Action&lt;/a&gt; (OCA) as part of my Turing AI Fellowship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to patients and OCA for their support in developing this work and its impact on my future research plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The report is available to download from &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cwcyau/turingaifellowship/blob/c38556ef96768a3b83744ea7c9eabe3290ffc623/mycancerai.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CIDER: an interpretable meta-clustering framework for single-cell RNA-seq data integration and evaluation</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-12-20_gbio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-12-20_gbio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our latest paper, based on the thesis work of former DPhil student Zhiyuan, has been published in Genome Biology. &lt;a href=&#34;https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-021-02561-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CIDER: an interpretable meta-clustering framework for single-cell RNA-seq data integration and evaluation&lt;/a&gt; describes a meta-clustering workflow based on inter-group similarity measures. We demonstrate that CIDER outperforms other scRNA-Seq clustering methods and integration approaches in both simulated and real datasets. Moreover, we show that CIDER can be used to assess the biological correctness of integration in real datasets, while it does not require the existence of prior cellular annotations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rarity: Discovering rare cell populations from single-cell imaging data</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-12-14_rarity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-12-14_rarity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Kaspar Martens will present his latest work at the NeurIPS Workshop &amp;ldquo;Learning Meaningful Representations of Life&amp;rdquo;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1r9TINxfXgB_cs4bOcT7ZYZjF5IMcb4X6/view&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Rarity: Discovering rare cell populations from single-cell imaging data&lt;/a&gt;. The work arises from his Turing-Crick Biomedical Award which supports a collaboration between the Alan Turing Institute and the Ciccarelli Group at Kings College London and the Francis Crick Institute.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yau receives award for ovarian cancer research</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-11-20_chfwrf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-11-20_chfwrf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.chfwrf.org/info/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Columbia Hospital For Women Research Foundation&lt;/a&gt; have awarded &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/admin&#34;&gt;Christopher Yau&lt;/a&gt; the prize for most impactful paper in 2020 in the field of obstetrical and gynecologic and breast disease. The prize consisted of a $5,000 to a charity of Chris and Ahmed&amp;rsquo;s choosing and they selected &lt;a href=&#34;https://ovarian.org.uk/about-us/about-oca/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ovarian Cancer Action&lt;/a&gt; who co-funded the original work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cell.com/cancer-cell/pdf/S1535-6108%2820%2930042-8.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Repertoire of Serous Ovarian Cancer Non-genetic Heterogeneity Revealed by Single-Cell Sequencing of Normal Fallopian Tube Epithelial Cells.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; was a collaboration with the Ovarian Cancer Laboratory, led by Professor Ahmed Ahmed at Oxford. Chris and Ahmed co-supervised former group student &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/hu&#34;&gt;Zhiyuan Hu&lt;/a&gt;, who was lead author.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Artificial Intelligence Webinar - Ovarian Cancer Action UK</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-11-10_oca_video/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-11-10_oca_video/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/admin&#34;&gt;Christopher Yau&lt;/a&gt; worked with &lt;a href=&#34;https://ovarian.org.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ovarian Cancer Action UK&lt;/a&gt; to put together a webinar on his research for patients and the public. You can find the video on Youtube: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kQ8m4L15GYM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;What is artificial intelligence and what does it mean for cancer research?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New study in JCI Insights</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-05-04_ici_mara/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-05-04_ici_mara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://insight.jci.org/articles/view/147929&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Adipocyte-like signature in ovarian cancer minimal residual disease identifies metabolic vulnerabilities of tumor-initiating cells&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wrh.ox.ac.uk/research/ovarian-cancer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Oxford Ovarian Cancer Cell Lab&lt;/a&gt; has been featured on the cover of JCI Insight. The work used methods developed by former group student &lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/campbell&#34;&gt;Kieran Campbell&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New study in Clinical Cancer Research</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-01-14_ccr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-01-14_ccr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With collaborators in the Oxford Ovarian Cancer Lab and Imperial College London, Zhiyuan Hu has identified that OxC-defined EMT-high SOCs carry particularly poor prognosis independent of established clinical parameters. She found these tumours are associated with high frequency of immunosuppressive macrophages, suggesting a potential therapeutic target to improve clinical outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://clincancerres.aacrjournals.org/content/early/2021/01/12/1078-0432.CCR-20-2782&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Link to paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turing AI Acceleration Fellowship</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/event/turingai/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/event/turingai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We aim to develop novel AI-driven predictive models that will allow us to describe how cancers evolve at the molecular level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aim to exploit the fact that cancers, whilst never exactly identical, often share similar development trajectories which we can learn about by collating information from across deep high-resolution molecular profiles of many cancers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By embedding our extensive biological knowledge of cancer within AI models, we will develop intelligent systems that will produce predictions that are more realistic, interpretable and better explain the progression of cancers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will help to improve the efficiency of drug development, decisions on treatment and to provide patients with more information about their illness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lead Investigator:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/admin/&#34;&gt;Christopher Yau&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turing AI Acceleration Fellowship</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-11-27_turingai/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-11-27_turingai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Christopher Yau has been awarded a 5-year Turing AI Acceleration Fellowship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Turing AI Acceleration Fellowships are part of the government’s AI sector deal investment in Turing AI fellowships, recommended by the independent 2017 UK AI Review, whose report ‘Growing the artificial intelligence industry in the UK,’ was co-authored by Reguis Professor of Computer Science at Southampton, Dame Wendy Hall, and Jérôme Pesenti, now Vice President of AI at Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/20-million-boost-for-world-class-ai-research-could-transform-cancer-treatment-and-save-lives&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UK Government Press Release: &amp;ldquo;£20 million boost for world class AI research could transform cancer treatment and save lives&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ukri.org/news/new-turing-ai-fellows-to-deliver-world-class-ai-research/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UKRI Press Release: &amp;ldquo;New Turing AI fellows to deliver world-class AI research&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-55099620&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BBC: &amp;ldquo;AI &amp;lsquo;doctor&amp;rsquo;s assistant&amp;rsquo; among projects given £20m&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scientists closer to finding the cell of origin for ovarian cancer</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-09-28_zh/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-09-28_zh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Former DPhil student Zhiyuan with the Ovarian Cancer Lab have created a new public engagement video showcasing our work on single cell sequencing of ovarian cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/oxfordahmedlab/status/1310686724402622464?s=20&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Scientists closer to finding the cell of origin for ovarian cancer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Convolutional filtering for mutation signatures</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/event/convsig/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/event/convsig/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mutation signatures are the hallmarks of mutagenic processes in cancer that can provide clues about the biochemical mechanisms by which DNA is altered in cancer. The extraction of such signatures from next generation sequencing data has traditionally been formulated as an unsupervised learning problem and solved using non-negative matrix factorization. We present an entirely novel approach based on convolutional filtering, inspired by technologies used in computer vision and image processing for genomic data analysis. We show that our approach has state-of-the-art performance compared to standard methods but also generalizes to allow consideration of larger sequence contexts using deep layering of convolutional networks providing a tool that could potentially reveal the impact of high-level genome structure on mutational density.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Researchers:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/feng/&#34;&gt;Yun Feng&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Precision medicine and individual-level cancer driver genes</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/event/cancer-drivers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/event/cancer-drivers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The identification of cancer-promoting genetic alterations is challenging particularly in highly unstable and heterogeneous cancers. In collaboration with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.crick.ac.uk/research/labs/francesca-ciccarelli&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ciccarelli Lab&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.crick.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Francis Crick Institute&lt;/a&gt; we have developed a machine learning algorithm to identify cancer genes in individual patients considering all types of damaging alterations simultaneously. Analysing 261 EACs from the OCCAMS Consortium, we discover helper genes that, alongside well-known drivers, promote cancer. We confirm the robustness of our approach in 107 additional EACs. Unlike recurrent alterations of known drivers, these cancer helper genes are rare or patient-specific. However, they converge towards perturbations of well-known cancer processes. Recurrence of the same process perturbations, rather than individual genes, divides EACs into six clusters differing in their molecular and clinical features. Experimentally mimicking the alterations of predicted helper genes in cancer and pre-cancer cells validates their contribution to disease progression, while reverting their alterations reveals EAC acquired dependencies that can be exploited in therapy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Researchers:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/nulsen/&#34;&gt;Joel Nulsen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/misetic//&#34;&gt;Hrvoje Misetic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RLevolution</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/event/rlevolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/event/rlevolution/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Genomic copy number evolution in cancer refers to the acquisition or loss of genome segments over time due to mutational processes in cancer that result in the loss of biological mechanisms for the maintenance of genome integrity in cells. Genome sequencing can allow us to detect these copy number alterations in cancer cells but do not directly inform us what the sequence of evolutionary events was that led to the present state of the cancer. We have developed a novel, first-of-its-kind reinforcement learning based approach for inferring evolutionary trajectories from genomic copy number profiles which we call \RLEvolution. We show that \RLEvolution is able to deconvolve the sequence of complex events that may occur during cancer evolution using a combination of simulated and real-world cancer datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Researchers:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/feng/&#34;&gt;Yun Feng&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ovarian Cancer</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/event/ovarian-cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/event/ovarian-cancer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are working with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wrh.ox.ac.uk/research/ovarian-cancer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ovarian Cancer Cell Laboratory&lt;/a&gt; led by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wrh.ox.ac.uk/team/ahmed-ahmed&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Professor Ahmed Ahsour Ahmed&lt;/a&gt; to unlock the molecular mechanisms underlying high-grade serous ovarian cancer (HGSOC) using genomics and bioinformatics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;premalignant-sox2-overexpression-in-the-fallopian-tubes-of-ovarian-cancer-patients&#34;&gt;Premalignant SOX2 overexpression in the fallopian tubes of ovarian cancer patients&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have discovered premalignant overexpression of SOX2 in the fallopian tubes of ovarian cancer patients which was nearly ubiquitous in HGSOCs. This was also a common feature in women with BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutations prior to ovarian cancer initiation. Thus, our data has important implications for screening, although it will need additional clinical evaluation to test the feasibility of quantitative detection of SOX2 expression or the expression of its downstream targets for this purpose. You can read the original research paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thelancet.com/journals/ebiom/article/PIIS2352-3964%2816%2930305-X/fulltext&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; as well as media reports &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dailymail.co.uk/health/article-3712949/Ovarian-cancer-detected-deadly-Scientists-identify-key-enzyme-makes-disease-spread.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.telegraph.co.uk/science/2016/07/28/ovarian-cancer-test-on-horizon-as-scientists-find-earliest-signs/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-unmasking-non-genetic-heterogeneity-through-by-single-cell-sequencing-of-fallopian-tube-epithelial-cells&#34;&gt;The unmasking non-genetic heterogeneity through by single-cell sequencing of fallopian tube epithelial cells&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently, we have used single cell sequencing to understand the inter-differentiation between cell states which promotes cancer cell survival under stress and fosters non-genetic heterogeneity (NGH). NGH is a surrogate of tumor resilience but its quantification is confounded by genetic heterogeneity. We showed that NGH can be accurately measured when informed by the molecular signatures of the normal cells of origin. We surveyed the transcriptomes of 4000 normal fallopian tube epithelial (FTE) cells, the cells of origin of serous ovarian cancer, and identified six FTE subtypes. We used subtype signatures to deconvolute SOC expression data and found substantial intra-tumor NGH that was previously unrecognized. Importantly, NGH-based stratification of ∼1700 tumors robustly predicted survival. Our findings lay the foundation for accurate prognostic and therapeutic stratification of SOC. You can read our Cancer Cell paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cell.com/cancer-cell/fulltext/S1535-6108%2820%2930042-8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and press coverage from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dailymail.co.uk/health/article-7987639/Ovarian-cancer-hope-discovery-six-types-cell-trigger-silent-killer.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Daily Mail&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Researchers:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/hu/&#34;&gt;Zhiyuan Hu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
