<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>machine learning | AI4Health</title>
    <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/tags/machine-learning/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://cwcyau.github.io/tags/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>machine learning</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright © 2019 by Christopher Yau. All Rights Reserved.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://cwcyau.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>machine learning</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/tags/machine-learning/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiple postdoctoral research positions available</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-08-01_postdocs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-08-01_postdocs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Due to recent grant successes, we currently have multiple postdoctoral positions available linked to the following projects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../project/turingai&#34;&gt;Turing AI Fellowship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../project/optimal&#34;&gt;OPTIMAL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../project/mumpredict&#34;&gt;MuM-PreDICT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../project/roche-antibody&#34;&gt;Roche RPF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suitable applicants should either have experience in developing statistical and/or machine learning methods or a background in mathematics and computational science that would enable them to learn relevant research approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interested applicants are advised to examine recent group publications and projects to understand the research methods that have been adopted within the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be substantial opportunities to develop your individual research profile, leadership capabilities and link to a range of academic, clinical and industry partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All enquiries about vacancies should be addressed to the 
&lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/admin&#34;&gt;Group Leader&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MuM-Predict</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/mumpredict/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/mumpredict/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The MuM-PreDiCT project has been successful in the funding call from the Strategic Priorities Fund (SPF): Tackling multimorbidity at scale: Understanding disease clusters, determinants &amp;amp; biological pathways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Strategic Priorities Fund (SPF) initiative, is jointly funded by the UKRI – MRC and the Department of Health and Social Care (DHSC), through the National Institute for Health Research (NIHR).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project will study and improve maternity care for women who are also managing two or more long-term health conditions. These can be both physical conditions, such as diabetes and raised blood pressure, and mental health conditions such as depression and anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our research team will develop statistical machine learning methods to analyse electronic health records from across all four nations comprising the UK. We will find out how many women have two or more long-term health conditions that presented before pregnancy and what health conditions they have. We will try and identify if factors such as age, weight, cultural or social background, level of education and number of previous pregnancies influences this. We will also find out which health conditions group together (cluster) during pregnancy, which clusters are most common and whether some clusters affect some women more than others.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OPTIMAL</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/optimal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/optimal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The OPTIMAL study is three-year study funded by the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nihr.ac.uk/documents/artificial-intelligence-for-multiple-long-term-conditions-aim-programme-research-collaboration-stage-2-minutes/27578s&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NIHR AI for Multimorbidity&lt;/a&gt; and is a collaboration with the Universities of Birmingham and St Andrews with CPRD and University Hospitals Birmingham.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this study our group will develop novel artificial intelligence technologies to study electronic health records of individuals with two or more conditions known as &amp;ldquo;complex multimorbidity&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our aim is to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find the mix of diseases and drug treatments that interact over time to worsen or improve a patient’s health.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predict the next disease that people might develop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find drugs that help more than one disease.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work with patients, the public and health professionals to produce computer programs to help doctors improve the choice of drugs in patients with cMM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ICML 2021</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-07-18_icml_2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-07-18_icml_2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to PhD student 
&lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/danks&#34;&gt;Dominic Danks&lt;/a&gt; whose paper 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://proceedings.mlr.press/v139/danks21a.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BasisDeVAE: Interpretable Simultaneous Dimensionality Reduction and Feature-Level Clustering with Derivative-Based Variational Autoencoders&lt;/a&gt;. has been accepted for presentation at the International Conference for Machine Learning 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roche ML for Antibody Design</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/roche-antibody/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/roche-antibody/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a new two-year collaboration with Roche, the group will be supporting a Roche Postdoctoral Fellowship in the development of antibodies. We will make use of Roche&#39;s existing antibody data to develop machine-learning models generating sequences of antibodies with desired biophysical properties. Our aims are to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop machine learning models that ingest in-house antibody engineering data on antibodies to generate novel sequences with increased likelihood of desired biophysical properties,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Iteratively apply methods to antibody datasets,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborate with experimental teams to select and test model-generated candidate sequences in the wet lab,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Embed machine learning models in discovery processes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New study in American Journal of Drug Alcohol Abuse</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-01-11_opioid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2021-01-11_opioid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Increasing rates of opioid-related overdose have been identified globally. Treatment for opioid use disorders (OUD) includes medications for opioid use disorder (MOUD) alongside behavioral support. In this study we use statistical analysis and machine learning to show that the Breaking Free Online program may reduce opioid use and improve biopsychosocial functioning in individuals with OUD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33428458/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Link to paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turing AI Acceleration Fellowship</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-11-27_turingai/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-11-27_turingai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Christopher Yau has been awarded a 5-year Turing AI Acceleration Fellowship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Turing AI Acceleration Fellowships are part of the government’s AI sector deal investment in Turing AI fellowships, recommended by the independent 2017 UK AI Review, whose report ‘Growing the artificial intelligence industry in the UK,’ was co-authored by Reguis Professor of Computer Science at Southampton, Dame Wendy Hall, and Jérôme Pesenti, now Vice President of AI at Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/20-million-boost-for-world-class-ai-research-could-transform-cancer-treatment-and-save-lives&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UK Government Press Release: &amp;ldquo;£20 million boost for world class AI research could transform cancer treatment and save lives&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ukri.org/news/new-turing-ai-fellows-to-deliver-world-class-ai-research/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UKRI Press Release: &amp;ldquo;New Turing AI fellows to deliver world-class AI research&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-55099620&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BBC: &amp;ldquo;AI &amp;lsquo;doctor&#39;s assistant&amp;rsquo; among projects given £20m&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turing AI Acceleration Fellowship</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/turingai/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/turingai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We aim to develop novel AI-driven predictive models that will allow us to describe how cancers evolve at the molecular level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aim to exploit the fact that cancers, whilst never exactly identical, often share similar development trajectories which we can learn about by collating information from across deep high-resolution molecular profiles of many cancers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By embedding our extensive biological knowledge of cancer within AI models, we will develop intelligent systems that will produce predictions that are more realistic, interpretable and better explain the progression of cancers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will help to improve the efficiency of drug development, decisions on treatment and to provide patients with more information about their illness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lead Investigator:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/admin/&#34;&gt;Christopher Yau&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting guidelines to report the use of AI in clinical trials </title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-09-09_consortai/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-09-09_consortai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The CONSORT-AI and SPIRIT-AI Steering Groups (including Christopher Yau) have published their guidelines for conducting and reporting on clinical trials for AI interventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-020-1069-z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Setting guidelines to report the use of AI in clinical trials&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Postdoc Opportunity with HDRUK</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-07-02_hdruk_mo/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-07-02_hdruk_mo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A new postdoc opportunity with myself and Dr Mike Inouye is available based in Cambridge:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jobs.cam.ac.uk/job/26181/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Health Data Research UK (HDRUK) Multi-omics Consortium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AISTATS 2020</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-01-17_kaspar/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2020-01-17_kaspar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to 
&lt;a href=&#34;../../authors/kaspar&#34;&gt;Kaspar Martens&lt;/a&gt; who has had two papers accepted into 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aistats.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;AISTATS 2020&lt;/a&gt;. Papers to be published soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ICML 2019 SUCCESS!</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2019-07-01_icml/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/post/2019-07-01_icml/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A paper by Kaspar Martens and group alumni Kieran Campbell Covariate GPLVM has been accepted for presentation at the International Conference on Machine Learning.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Convolutional filtering for mutation signatures</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/convsig/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/convsig/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mutation signatures are the hallmarks of mutagenic processes in cancer that can provide clues about the biochemical mechanisms by which DNA is altered in cancer. The extraction of such signatures from next generation sequencing data has traditionally been formulated as an unsupervised learning problem and solved using non-negative matrix factorization. We present an entirely novel approach based on convolutional filtering, inspired by technologies used in computer vision and image processing for genomic data analysis. We show that our approach has state-of-the-art performance compared to standard methods but also generalizes to allow consideration of larger sequence contexts using deep layering of convolutional networks providing a tool that could potentially reveal the impact of high-level genome structure on mutational density.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Researchers:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/feng/&#34;&gt;Yun Feng&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Omics Network inference</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/monet/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/monet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dynamic alterations in gene expression programs during cell differentiation are regulated by the interplay of ubiquitous and tissue-specific transcription factors, and the epigenetic regulatory machinery. A mechanistic understanding can be postulated based on time-course multi-omics genome-wide measurements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We developed a novel Bayesian nonparametric regression approach called &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt;ulti-&lt;strong&gt;O&lt;/strong&gt;mics &lt;strong&gt;NET&lt;/strong&gt;work inference (MONET) for high-dimensionality multi-modal data integration to quantify the temporally dependent forces driving development and investigate by perturbation effects. Sparsity-inducing priors regularise the TF-gene interaction network and a Dirichlet process prior to regulate the number of participating TFs. This gives rise to a Bayesian nonparametric model where the number of TFs are learnt from data and not specified a priori. Statistical inference is performed in a Bayesian setting using an implementation of Hamiltonian Monte Carlo (HMC)-derived No-U Turn Sampler (NUTS) in STAN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We show that MONET is able to extract accurate time-dependent TF-gene interaction networks and assess the importance of each TF for the different stages in haematopoietic development. Our model allows us to make predictions on the importance of specific TF over time and under different perturbation settings. Based on this we can create hypotheses for intervention to improve efficiency or halt development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Researchers:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/rana/&#34;&gt;Anas Rana&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neural Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/neural-decomp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/neural-decomp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Neural network models for dimensionality reduction, such as Variational AutoEncoders (VAEs), can identify latent low-dimensional structures embedded within high-dimensional data. These low-dimensional representations can provide some insight into patterns within datasets but their interpretation relies on how these map back on the original feature set. However the latter requires interpreting what the decoder network has learnt which makes it challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, we have focused on understanding the sources of variation in Conditional VAEs. Our goal is to &lt;em&gt;decompose&lt;/em&gt; the feature-level variation in high-dimensional data through disentanglement of additive and interactions effects of latent variables and fixed inputs. We propose to achieve this through the &lt;em&gt;Neural Decomposition&lt;/em&gt; - an adaptation of the well-known concept of variance decomposition from classical statistics to deep learning models. We show that &lt;em&gt;identifiable&lt;/em&gt; Neural Decomposition relies on training models subject to constraints on the marginal properties of the neural networks whilst naive implementations will lead to non-identifiable models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Researchers:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/kaspar/&#34;&gt;Kaspar Maertens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RLevolution</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/rlevolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/rlevolution/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Genomic copy number evolution in cancer refers to the acquisition or loss of genome segments over time due to mutational processes in cancer that result in the loss of biological mechanisms for the maintenance of genome integrity in cells. Genome sequencing can allow us to detect these copy number alterations in cancer cells but do not directly inform us what the sequence of evolutionary events was that led to the present state of the cancer. We have developed a novel, first-of-its-kind reinforcement learning based approach for inferring evolutionary trajectories from genomic copy number profiles which we call \RLEvolution. We show that \RLEvolution is able to deconvolve the sequence of complex events that may occur during cancer evolution using a combination of simulated and real-world cancer datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Researchers:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/feng/&#34;&gt;Yun Feng&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Automatic BioData Scientist</title>
      <link>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/neural-odes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://cwcyau.github.io/project/neural-odes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mathematical models of disease evolution seek to specify the complex mechanistic relationships between many measurable quantities over space and time. However, as our capability to generate experimental data improves, our ability to conceive of appropriate mathematical descriptions to describe biological phenomena has become a bottleneck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of machine learning is to “learn” complex dependencies automatically within data sets.  Neural networks (NNs) have been at the forefront of recent advances by offering a means of parametrising complex functional mapping between data and its representations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Novel computational machinery have enabled NN approaches to scale to the analysis of unprecedently large datasets and provide versatility over standard modelling approaches. However, despite their successes in a range of applications, in biomedical research, NNs are often derided for their “black box” discoveries, lack of interpretability and the need for unrealistic quantities of training data. Such criticisms often overlook the fact that default NN structures express no explicit assumptions about the problems on which they are applied and they are often used as generic data mining devices for discovery purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, there is a clear opportunity for the development of novel NN approaches that combine scalability and versatility with the capability of learning the physically realistic constraints that are embedded in hand-crafted mathematical models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project seeks to investigate the methodological foundations for what could form an &lt;em&gt;Automated BioData Scientist&lt;/em&gt; (AutoBioDataSci) platform. We would like to develop learning algorithms that can capture biological laws and encapsulate them in such a way that such knowledge can be transfer to new problems. This major project involves inter-linking representation learning theory with transfer and meta-learning as well as having its roots embedded in the biological scientific discovery process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Researchers:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/danks/&#34;&gt;Dominic Danks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cwcyau.github.io/authors/kaspar/&#34;&gt;Kaspar Maertens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
